<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons preached by the reuerend father in God the Bishop of Chichester the first at Paules Crosse. The second at Westminster before the Queenes Maiestie.</title>
            <author>Curteys, Richard, 1532?-1582.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19722</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851288</idno>
  <idno type="VID">16559</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240897696</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 6141</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S116071</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99851288e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1601:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons preached by the reuerend father in God the Bishop of Chichester the first at Paules Crosse. The second at Westminster before the Queenes Maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Curteys, Richard, 1532?-1582.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[106] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Man, and W. Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G (-G6-8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:1"/>
            <p>Two Sermons preached by the reuerend father in God Richard Bishop of Chichester, the first at Paules Crosse.</p>
            <p>The second at West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster before the Queenes Maiestie.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by T. Man, and W. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome.</hi> Anno. 1584</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:2"/>
            <head>The first Sermon preached <hi>at Paules Crosse on Sonday being the</hi> fourth day of March. 1576.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>APOC. 12.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>There was a greate wonder in heauen, a woman was clothed with the Sun, &amp; the Moon was vnder hir feete, and vpon hir head was a Crowne of xij. starres, and she was with child, and she cried, &amp; was pained to be deliuered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>And there was another wonder in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And behold, a greate red Dragon had seuen heads, and ten hornes, &amp; seuen crownes vpon his heads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>And his taile did drawe the third parte of the starres of Heauen, and the Dragon stood before the woman which was to be deliuered, that when she should be deliuered, he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure the child.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>And she brought forth a man child which was to rule all nations in an iron rod. And hir child was taken vp to God and to his Throne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>And the woman fled into a wildernesse to a place prepared of God, to feede hir there a thousand two hundreth and three score dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>And there was a great battell in Heauē, Michaell and his Angels fought with the
<pb facs="tcp:16559:3"/> Dragon, and the Dragon fought and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but they were not able to stande: neither was their place any more to be founde in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>And that great Dragon, that old serpēt which is called the Diuell, and Sathan, was throwne vpon the earth, and his Angels with him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8 <hi>And I heard a great voice in Heauen, saying: Now is wrought saluation &amp; strength and the kingdome of God, and the power of his Christ: for the accuser of our brethren is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne which accused them in the sighte of God day and night.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9 <hi>And they ouercame him throughe the bloud of the lamb and the words of their testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, &amp; they loued not their liues vnto death, and therefore reioyce in Heauen and yee that dwell therein.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:3"/>
               <head>❧ The first Sermon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the consent of the most of the auncient Fathers and late writers: this wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mā doth signifie y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church or the people of God cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen to saluation. The greate red Dragon signifieth Sathan. Michaell signifieth Christ: and his Angels the true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
               <p>This portion of Scripture is as it were a Picture of the people of God, fighting in the wildernesse of this world against Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and his limmes, vnder the Banner and guiding of Christ Iesus their grand captaine, and of that victorie whiche this Michael, this mightie and strong conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer doth get vnto his people ouer their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid enimies.</p>
               <list>
                  <label>The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall points bée these.</label>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. The apparrel of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church</item>
                        <item>2. The conditiō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church.</item>
                        <item>3. The victory of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> church.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>For the first generall point. The first particular lessō of that is the Sun, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel
<pb facs="tcp:16559:4"/> of the Church. The sunne Messias, the sun of righteousnes, Christ Iesus the righteous.</p>
               <p>For like as the sun doth as it were cloth and kéepe warme: and comfort al the crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of this world: so Christe the Sun of righteousnes, doth cloth, kéepe warme, &amp; comfort the Saints of God vpon Earth. For to the sanctified and chosē <hi>Romaines</hi> &amp; <hi>Galathians</hi> (faith the Apostle) <hi>Christū</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 13. 14. Bal. 3. 28.</note>
                  <hi>induistis,</hi> you haue put on Christ and clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed your selues with Christ. And to the same effect to the <hi>Ephesians</hi> to be sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 14.</note>
                  <hi>Awake thou that sleepest and rise frō the dead, &amp; Christ shal shine vnto thee.</hi> The beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and blesse of this apparel wil the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appéere, if we behold our naked and ougly cursed state without Christ.</p>
               <p>Man by nature is carnall, solde vnder sin, the bondman of sin: and the reward of sin is death. Man by nature is the childe of Gods wrath, the vessel of Gods wrath <hi>Remember</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>that you were</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 7. 14. Ro. 6. 2. Eph. 2. 3. Eph. 2. 12.</note>
                  <hi>without Christ, being aliants from the commō welth of Israell, straungers from the testament of promise, hauing no hope, and being without God in this world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Iohn</hi> setteth the cursed nakednesse
<pb facs="tcp:16559:4"/> &amp; the blessed apparrell togither in the first<note place="margin">Apo. 1. 5.</note> chapter of the Reuelation. <hi>Grace and peace</hi> (saith he) <hi>be vnto you from Iesus Christ, who hath loued vs, and washed vs from our sins in his owne bloud, and made vs Kinges and Priests vnto God his Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firste wée are to learne, what hath<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 4.</note> delyuered vs and clothed vs. The looue of GOD, the riche grace and mercie of GOD in Christe. For GOD which is greate in mercye, for his greate loue wherewith he loued vs, euen when wée were dead by sins, hath quickned vs togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Christ.</p>
               <p>Next we are to learne, from what wée are deliuered. From the bōdage of sinne, from the terror of death, from the fearful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of gods wrath. That is from euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting dānation &amp; torments vnspeakeable.</p>
               <p>Thirdly we are to learne, to what we are deliuered. To be Kings and Priests vnto god, to kil our beastly affectiōs with faith in the death and merits of Christ, to burne thē with the heat of loue, that is, to present both our bodies &amp; soules, a quick,<note place="margin">Ro. 12. 1.</note> holy and swéet sacrifice vnto God, to liue before God in holines and righteousnes al the daies of our life.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yee are</hi> (saith S. <hi>Peter) a spiritual house an holy priesthood for to offer vp spirituall sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2 9.</note>
                  <hi>acceptable vnto God, throughe Christ. Yee are a chosen generatiō, ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ial priesthood, a holy nation, a people which are won, that yee should show the vertues of him that called you out of darkenes into his maruailous light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus saith the holy and true, whiche hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apo 3. 7.</note>
                  <hi>the key of Dauid, which openeth and no man shutteth, which shutteth, and no man openeth: because thou sayest I am rich and full of goods</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apo. 3. 17.</note>
                  <hi>&amp; neede nothing, &amp; knowest not that thou art wretched and miserable, and poore and naked: I councell thee to buy of me golde tried in the fire that thou maiest be rich, and white raimēt that thy filthie nakednes do not appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re, &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint thine eies with eie salue that thou maist see.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Christiās be clothed with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bright Son Christ Iesus, and made a spirituall house &amp; holy préesthood, not to defile their garmēts with sin, but to buy and receiue of Christ the Golde of liuely Faith, the white garment of righteousnes, and the ey salue of the knowledge of Gods word, that their light may shine before men, to win them to God, that they being the salt of the earth may season &amp; edifie their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:5"/> that they testifie vnto the worlde, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the children of God &amp; by good works may stop the mouthes of suche as would take any occasion to speake euil of the Gospell.</p>
               <p>The next particular lesson is. <hi>That the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eadeth the Moone vnder hir feet.</hi> The people of god do not care for the changeable &amp; fading goods of this worlde, which eb and flow, increase and decrease, and change as the moone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exhort them</hi> (saith Saint <hi>Paule</hi> vnto<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2. 17.</note>
                  <hi>Timothie) that are rich in this worlde, that they be not high minded, nor trust in vncertain riches, but in the liuing God (which giueth vs abundantly all things to enioy them) that they doe good, that they be rich in good workes, that they be rady to giue and glad to distribute, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vp for themselues a good foundation against the day to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Birth, beautie, riches, renowne and glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry of this world, be wel likened by a good father to an Auditors coūters, which sō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times represent an hūdred thousād poūds somtimes a thousād pounds, somtimes a shilling, somtimes a peny, somtimes they are laid aside for nothing. So the coūters and houses, and rich persons of the world
<pb facs="tcp:16559:6"/> somtimes they excéede somtimes they bée lesse, somtimes not worth the groūd that beareth them. And therfore that heathen Emperour <hi>Saladinus</hi> séemeth wiser than a great sort of Christians, which when he had gotten great victories▪ and great spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ouer great cities and countries, and after fel sicke, &amp; sawe that he must néedes dy, required that whē he should be caried to his tumb: there should be caried before him a faire white shéete vpon the point of a speare, and proclamation to be made.</p>
               <p>These are the rich spoiles which <hi>Saladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> carieth away of all his triumphes &amp; victories.</p>
               <p>And surely y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> great mē of this world shall one day become the Auditors Counters, and shal play <hi>Saladinus,</hi> they shal dy and cary away with thē nothing but a shrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding sheet: the wise men of this world shal one day become the Auditors Counters, and shall play <hi>Saladinus,</hi> they shall dye &amp; carry away with them nothing but a shrowding shéete. The rich men of thys world shall one day become the Auditors Counters, and shal play <hi>Saladinus,</hi> they shall dye and carry away with them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a shrowding shéet: and therfore
<pb facs="tcp:16559:6"/> the people of God doo treade these moones &amp; vanities vnder their féete, vse these out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward blessings of god to the glory of god, to the reliefe of the strangers, the widow the fatherlesse, the impotent, and such as cannot helpe themselues.</p>
               <p>In this treading &amp; vsing of these moones &amp; transitory goods doth God delight, for Christ setteth it down so in the great and▪ dreadfull last charge. <hi>You sawe mee hungry</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 35</note>
                  <hi>and gaue me meat▪ you sawe me thirsty &amp; gaue me drinke, you sawe me naked, and gaue mee clothing, you sawe me harbourlesse &amp; gaue me lodging, you sawe me sicke and in prison &amp; you ministred vnto me. And they shall say, Lord when did we feede thee, cloth thee or minister vnto thee? And he shall say, when you did it to any of these little ones. you did it vnto mee.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to good Saint <hi>Hieroms</hi> saying: féede Christ in the hungry, cloth Christ in the naked, lodge Christ in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> harbourlesse, minister vnto Christ in the stranger, in the widow, in the fatherlesse childe: and such as cannot helpe themselues.</p>
               <p>Histories make mention of a good duke of <hi>Subaudia</hi> called <hi>Amodeus,</hi> vnto whom certain Ambassadors from forraine prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces resorted, and after their publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires
<pb facs="tcp:16559:7"/> doone: they asked him, if he had any hounds, for they were desirous to sée some hūting with hounds. Yea quoth <hi>Amodae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> I haue a kennel of as good hounds as a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny in <hi>Europe,</hi> if you come early in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning you shal sée them. The Ambassadors came early in the morning, &amp; <hi>Amodaeus</hi> led them to the backside of his house, and there shewed them a great sorte of poore folke at breakfast. <hi>Atque hi sunt (inquit canes mei.</hi> These be my Houndes, with these doe I hunt. <hi>Amodoeus</hi> was a good hunts man, and hunted ful wel. <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the <hi>Centurion</hi> hunted w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these hounds,<note place="margin">Act. 10. 4.</note> and the Angel said vnto him, <hi>Thy praiers and thy almes haue climed vp to heauen, to the sight of God. He that giueth vnto the poore lē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 17</note>
                  <hi>vnto the Lord, and looke what he layeth out shall be paide him againe. Blessed is he that considereth the poore and needy, the Lord will</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 41. 1</note>
                  <hi>deliuer him in the time of trouble.</hi> Blessed, &amp; a thousād times blessed is he that for gods sake helpeth them that be in misery.</p>
               <p>There is now a necessary and a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table prouisiō to erect houses in boroughs and market townes, for suche as woulde work if they had it but cānot be set a work Further that work and hunt with <hi>Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16559:7"/> his hounds. Make no more account of your auditors counters, your birth, wis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, authoritie, riches, then <hi>Saladmus</hi> did: for they shal yéeld vp but a shrowding shéet. Hunt with <hi>Amodeus</hi> houndes, and remember that you can enioy but youre<note place="margin">Ex. 16. 20.</note> Ghomer. <hi>If you reserue any til the morning it will rot and be full of wormes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you haue prouided inoughe for your own family, bestow the rest of your Manna vpon hospitals, vpon poore schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, vpon mending highwaies and suche good déedes. Bestowe it in the day of your life vpon some good woork or other. If you think to lay vp any part of your Manna &amp; goods against to morrowe, againste an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, it will rot and be ful of wormes. The moths wil eat it, or the théeues will steal it: your prodigal posterity wil make it away, or one bad person or other wyll<note place="margin">Mat. 19. 6</note> haue it away. Therfore sée it wel bestow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed before your eies, and tread the moone &amp; glory of this world vnder your féete.</p>
               <p>The third lesson is, <hi>That the Church is crowned with xij. starres.</hi> In the firste of the reuelation, the holy Ghost doth saye, that the Son of man had in his hande se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen<note place="margin">Apo. 1. 16 Apo. 1. 20.</note> starres. And after he saith the starres
<pb facs="tcp:16559:8"/> be the Angels of the seuen Churches. And so in this place the xij. starres be the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of the xii. Churches. And because the number 7. and twelue be perfect num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: they signifie the Angels, Ambassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors or ministers of the vniuersal and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, according to the opniō of the most of the fathers both old and new. And to the same effect (saith Saint <hi>Paule) We are Ambassadors in the roume of Christ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Co. 5. 20</note>
                  <hi>euen as though God did beseech you through vs.</hi> So pray we you in Christes stead, that you would be reconciled vnto God. And the same Saint <hi>Paule. <hi>Let a man so esteeme</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 1</note>
                  <hi>vs euen as the Ministers of Christ and stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes of the mysteries of God.</hi> These starres, Ambassadours or Ministers bring to you the word of God, the way to your saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. These starres. Ambassadors, or mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes, bring to you the holy and blessed sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, the pledges and pawns of your saluation. And therefore they shoulde bée moste welcome and déere vnto you. But euen as the clouds doe many times hide the Starres, whiche shyne moste brighte: So the Clowdes of malice, and Couetousnes, &amp; Godlessenesse, doe hyde the Starres and ministers of the Gospel.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:8"/>
               <p>It is a world toe sée how welcome and déere the darke stars were which brought y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> doctrine of men and deuises of men. No lands were too much for thē, no estimatiō too great, no treasure too much. And nowe when the bright starres of the Gospell, bring the sincere word of God, the heauē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Manna and bread of our soules, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> path to the ioyes of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> celestial paradise, which<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 9</note> neither eie hath séene, nor eare hath heard nor tong can expresse, nor hart conceiue: euery little is too much for them, euerye one doth pine and grudge at them, euery meane man may, and doth carry vp and downe sclanders of them, reuile them in euery alehouse and tauern. God grāt that this contempt of Gods ministers be not a certaine token of the ripenes of sin, and a woful fall hard at hand.</p>
               <p>But yet ministers must not be discom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted,<note place="margin">Mat. 1. 19.</note> for the scholler may not bée better than his maister. Our Sauiour Christe was called a glutton, a drunkard, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of publicans and sinners, a woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker by <hi>Belzebub:</hi> and yet he was moste<note place="margin">Maht. 12. 24.</note> godly and did most godly. Though they call you what they can call you: cry you out against vice, cōdemne Epicures, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiuils
<pb facs="tcp:16559:9"/> and godlesse persons. Tell them sin is sin, vanitie vanitie, trueth trueth, &amp; vertue is vertue. Lifte vp youre voyces like trumpets, and shew the people their<note place="margin">Esa. 58. 1.</note> sinnes: shine like Starres in this darke world, &amp; you shall shine with your great<note place="margin">Apo. 22. 16.</note> morning star Christ Iesus in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
               <p>The fourth particular lesson is, <hi>That the Church trauaileth &amp; is pained to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered.</hi> The Church the spouse of Christe clothed with y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Sun of righteousnes (trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding vpon and neglecting the Moone, and chaunging ioyes of the worlde, crowned, with the starres and ministers of the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of man) cānot be idle nor carelesse nor cold, but is made careful and warme, and zealous of Gods truth. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> speaketh of this woman and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which saith. <hi>I held my tongue and spake</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Psal. 39. 2.</note>
                  <hi>nothing, I kept silence euen from good wordes, but it was paine and griefe to me, my hart was hot within me, &amp; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tle I was thus musing, the fire kindled, at the lust I spake with my mouth.</hi> As also the Churche saith againe in the<note place="margin">Psal. 119. 136. Psal. 119. 123. 139.</note> person of <hi>Dauid. <hi>Mine eies gush out with water, because men keepe not thy law. My eies are wasted away with looking for thy health
<pb facs="tcp:16559:9"/> and for the word of thy righteousnes. My zeale hath euen consumed me, because mine enimies haue forgotten thy cōmandements. It greeueth me when I see the transgressors, because they keepe not thy lawe.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our english Church (God be blessed) is clothed with the robe of Christ, professeth Christe truely, is crowned with infinite starres and good professors of his worde, and yet it is a wonder to sée howe colde the zeale of it is, how little hate of sinne it hath. In daies paste whosoeuer did tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and was pained to bring forth the worde of God and vertue and truth, was liked and furthered of al men. Bad persōs were generally hated and misliked. But now is the quite contrary. I meane not, nor I cannot say that there are so many or so great malefactors, as hath béene in other times: but this I may say and this I must say, that there is not the deuotion towards God, nor that loue of vertue, nor that hate of sin that was in the time of darkenes.</p>
               <p>A man is not liked because he dooth wel, nor misliked because he dooth euill. But now there is an Art to heape and throng a sorte into one faction, and they bend them
<pb facs="tcp:16559:10"/> selues to speake, and doo all the euill they can deuise by such as they mislike, be they neuer so good, and to speake and doe al the good they can, for such as they like, be they neuer so bad, yea though their badnes be marked to the eye.</p>
               <p>Remember therfore from whence you are fallen, and repent and doe the firste workes, or else, he that holdeth the seuen starres in his right hand, and walketh in<note place="margin">Apo, 2. 5.</note> the mids of the 7 golden candlesticks, wil come shortly &amp; remooue your cādlesticks out of their places. God grant vs al light and loue, one and other to repent. And as we would séeme to wear the rich apparell of the Gospell of Christ, and to be starres in this Church of Christ, that so we may trauel and be pained to be deliuered, that is, to be zelous and redy to set forth gods glory, and to tread downe and suppresse vice, Idolatrie, and vanitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The second part.</head>
               <p>THe second principal point is, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Church to be maligned of Sathan, and protected by God. As the
<pb facs="tcp:16559:10"/> people of God be zealous and earnest to sow the word of God and plant religion:<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 11.</note> so the dragon and sathan be as watchfull and painefull to deuoure the frute.<note place="margin">Mat. 4. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Adam was no sooner borne, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than assalted him,</l>
                  <l>Christ was no sooner borne, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than tempted him.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Dragon is great and red, &amp; hath many heds, &amp; many hornes, and many crownes, full of deceit, craft malice, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, pride, power, might and fiercenesse, and by worldly promotiō, luker, fauor &amp; other flattering fancies, he entāgleth ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny wise men, and casteth many Starres downe to the ground, and plucketh them clean from Christ and maketh them car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and vngodly in al their wisdome, stu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and workes. And he standeth euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the womā traueling, euermore way<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting his pray, where the gospel is sincerly taught. The children of God be no sooner born again and renewed by the spirit of god, but he séeketh to deuoure the fruit of grace sowne in their hartes. He vseth all crafts, policies, and engines to take the word from the hart, lest the people belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:16559:11"/> it would be saued.</p>
               <p>If the woman: if the people of God sléep but a little or giue thēselues to carelesnes, the enuious man commeth, this Dragon<note place="margin">Ma. 13. 25</note> commeth and soweth the tares of Sin to choke the séed of religion, which the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of God had sowed before. He goeth<note place="margin">Iob. 1. 7.</note> about the lād and walketh through it. He is a painful visitor, he visiteth &amp; search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth euery corner of his circuit: he sifteth al the people, euen as wheat is sifted, &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Luc. 22. 31</note> about to turne al to chaffe of vanity &amp; pleasure. This watchfulnes and crafty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the dragon should teach vs also to be watchful: for so reasoneth saint <hi>Peter. <hi>Bee sober and watch, for your aduersary the</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 8.</note>
                  <hi>deuil goeth about like a roring Lyon, seeking whome he may deuoure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Watche we should to continencie, for such as will be drunken either with the pomp, or port, or pleasure of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world: are sure to be deuoured of the dragō, Watch<note place="margin">Mat. 1426</note> we should to praier, lest we fal into temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation. For those that forbeare fasting &amp; praier are easily tempted of the Dragon. Watch we should al in our calling that<note place="margin">Ma. 25. 45 Luc. 16. 2.</note> we may be found good stuards and giue a
<pb facs="tcp:16559:11"/> good account, when we shal leaue the stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardship of this life.</p>
               <p>Ministers ought to watch and to crye out zealously and boldly against all kind of sin, in al kind of persōs without respect</p>
               <p>Magistrates ought to watch &amp; to beate down al kind of sin &amp; punish al kind of sin in al kind of persons without respect. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery householder ought to watch to sée y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> not only himself, his wife and Children, but also his seruants, yea the least boy &amp; girle that is in his house be brought vp in the knowledge &amp; feare of God: for if any of them perish for lacke of instructiō, that housholder shall answere for their bloud, and be deuoured of the Dragon. Watch ye nobles to the defence of religiō, trueth, and Iustice. Watche ye Ministers to the teaching of religion, trueth and Iustice. Watch ye Iudges, Iustices, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates, to the execution of religiō, trueth and Iustice: watch England, watch Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to thankfulnes to God. least the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Child of the faithfull woman (Gods holy word) be once again deuoured of the dragon. And to comfort you against this watchfulnes and cruelnesse of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:12"/> is the goodnes of God, a fortresse and bulwark. For first notwithstandyng the dragon be so watchful, and cruel and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to deuoure: God againe is ready, yea a thousand times more redy to preserue: he defendeth his, blesseth and preserueth his for the woman brought forth hir Childe and it was takē vp to god &amp; to his throne God brought the woman his Churche of<note place="margin">Exo. 14.</note>
                  <hi>Israel,</hi> great with child out of <hi>Egipt.</hi> The dragon stood ready by the <hi>Amalekits, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diants, Moabites,</hi> &amp; such other to deuoure the Child. But the Childe, Gods lawe was brought forth: for the heathen were<note place="margin">Psa. 80. 3.</note> cast out, &amp; Gods vine planted, God made rowme for it and it filled the lande. The hils were couered with the shadowes of it, and the boughes thereof were like the goodly Ceder trées: she stretched forth hir branches vnto y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> sea and hir boughs vnto the riuer, that is, god tooke it to his throne and protection.</p>
               <p>The woman the primatiue churche tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed, and was pained to bring forth hir child the Gospell of Christ Iesus. The Dragon stood still by <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas</hi> by <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herode,</hi> by <hi>Simon Magus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 20. 7.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16559:12"/> the sorcerer, <hi>Alexander</hi> the coppersmith,<note place="margin">Act. 8. 9. 2. Tim. 4. 12. Act. 10. 24 Act. 2. 47.</note> and <hi>Demetrius</hi> the siluer smith to deuour the Child. But the word of God increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and the number of the disciples mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied greatly, and the Lord added to the congregation dayly such as should be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, &amp; tooke the Gospell to his throne and protection. The <hi>Germain</hi> church trauai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and pained to bring forth hir Childe the Gospel of Christ. The Churches of <hi>Poleland, Denmark, Sueueland, England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> haue trauailed &amp; bin pained to bring forth the Childe, the Gospell of Christ Iesus. The dragon hath stood rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Italian <hi>Caiphas,</hi> the Romish scri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes and pharyses, their <hi>Pilates:</hi> their <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods,</hi> their <hi>Simons▪</hi> their <hi>Alexanders</hi> and <hi>Demetriusses</hi> to deuoure the Child. But the Gospell doth flourish and prosper in these lands, and god hath taken it to hys throne and protection. The Churches of <hi>France &amp; Flanders</hi> doo trauell and are pained to bring forth their Child the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Christ Iesus. The great red Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon doth bestur himself with al his heds, hornes and crownes, powers and crafts, limmes and partakers, to deuoure their
<pb facs="tcp:16559:13"/> Childe the Gospell of Christ Iesus. But<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 2. 10</note> it shal be borne and prosper, and god shal take it to his throne &amp; protection. For the deuill may imprisō them &amp; trouble them ten daies, but in the end the faithful shal<note place="margin">3. Esdr. 4.</note> haue the crowne of life, and trueth shall preuaile.</p>
               <p>The next step of Gods goodnes, is the rod of Discipline, for the direction of his Church and people. For as he begetteth his Children with the preaching of the word: so he appointeth a rod &amp; Discipline<note place="margin">Pro. 22. 15</note> for the direction of his people. Whē folly is tied to the Childes hart: the rod of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection must take it away. Childrē of the best nature wil leaue their bookes &amp; play and fal togither by the eares, if the rod of correction be not shewed to thē. And the people of the best nature wil leaue y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> book of Religion and spend their time in idle play and pastime, or fall togither by the eares, and to contention if the rod of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection doe not stay such folly. The wise man curseth that wood of the which Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges<note place="margin">Sap. 14. 7.</note> be made to draw men from the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to the creature: but blesseth that wood by the which Iustice is done, and men be
<pb facs="tcp:16559:13"/> drawne from folly to the feare of God.</p>
               <p>Gods people be shéepe: the shepeheard néedeth a whistle, and he néedeth a Dog<note place="margin">Psa. 79. 13</note> and a hooke, that such shéepe as will not cōe in with whistling, may be either bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in with a Dog, or drawne in with a hooke. The preaching of the word of God is the whistling. such as wil not cōe into the fold of saluation by the whistle of the word, must be cōpelled to come in by the Dog and hooke of discipline. The mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters doo sing &amp; play vnto the people with the harp of the word. But the people wil<note place="margin">Ma. 11. 17</note> not daūce after the mesures of the word.</p>
               <p>The ministers mourn vnto the people mooued with the iudgements of gods Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice: but the people wéep not for their sin and for the wrath of God comming: whē neither the blessings of God nor the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of God wil preuaile: the iron rod of discipline is requisite to bruse the stonye<note place="margin">Ose 2. 6.</note> hartes, and cause them to wéepe and to daunce after the measures of the worde. When the railes of the law woulde not hold the straying shéepe of <hi>Israell</hi> in the pasture of the word: God himself appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thē the hedge of thorny discipline.
<pb facs="tcp:16559:14"/> The guests would not come to the kings feast by bidding, and therefore the King<note place="margin">Luc. 14. 23</note> took order with his seruāts to cōpel them The feast is Religion, the hearing of the word, the receiuing of the sacramēt. Bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, is exhortation out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> word of god. Compulsion, is the iron rod of discipline which must then be vsed when exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wil not serue. <hi>Miriam, Moises</hi> sister was bidden to the Kings feast, by many<note place="margin">Nu. 12. 10.</note> blessings of God. But she rose from the table, &amp; therfore the rod of leprosie cōpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hir to come in again. The lost son left<note place="margin">Luc. 15. 12</note> the kings feast, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> church of god, but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rod of pouerty cōpelled him to come in again</p>
               <p>Our maister Christe ioyned the worde<note place="margin">Ma. 21. 13.</note> &amp; discipline togither. <hi>My house</hi> (quoth he) <hi>shal be called the house of praier, but you haue made it a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n of theeues. And he made a whip</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ion. 2. 15</note>
                  <hi>&amp; whipped the buiers &amp; sellers out of the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple.</hi> The great King and God Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, hath biddē al Englishmē to the feast of his word and sacraments by his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants helth, welth, cōcord, his ministers &amp; preachers. But some will not come to the feast, some sit downe &amp; tast not of the meat, some snatch a little, and by and by
<pb facs="tcp:16559:14"/> run away: the ministers doo whistle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thē, pipe to them, sing to them, mourne to them, pitch the railes of God his lawe, and preach the word and Gospel to them. But they will neither daunce or mourne folly is tied to the childrens harts: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is now requisite that Iudges and nobles, and counsellers, whiche haue in this common welth the authority &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenance, should draw out the rod of disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and take folly from these childrens harts. It is now requisite for councellors for Iudges and nobles, to vse the word of Iustice the hooke of discipline, the thorns of punishment, the iron rod of correction, &amp; the whip of seueritie to drawe in these vnthankful guests, and to kéep them into this most blessed feast, to cause high and low to come into Gods house, to heare the word of God, and to receiue his holy sacraments, the pawnes and pledges of our redemption, and more worth than al the treasures of the world.</p>
               <p>The third step of Gods goodnes is the prouidēce of god, which prepareth a place for his church in the wildernesse, and fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his people in the wide world, a thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sand,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:15"/> two hundred and thrée score dayes.</p>
               <p>God fed the Children of <hi>Israell</hi> fortie yéeres in the wildernes, with bread from<note place="margin">Exo. 1. 61. Exo. 17. 6</note> heauen and water out of the Rocke. God fed the children of his primatiue Church in the wildernes of this world in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> daies of <hi>Nero, Dioclesian, Iulianus</hi> and others, with the water and bread of his mightie power, a thousād, two hundred and thrée score daies. God fed the widow of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptha</hi> with a little meale in a barel and a little oyle in a cruse, till there fell raine vpon the earth. God fed the widdow his church of <hi>Europe,</hi> with a litle meale, and a litle oile of his word, from the Empire of <hi>Phocas</hi> to the Empire of <hi>Sigismonde,</hi> til the raine of his grace fel vpon <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, Germany, England</hi> and other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>There was in Iewry a prophet called Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuck,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Da. 14. 33.</note>
                  <hi>which had made potage, &amp; broken bread in a deepe platter, and was going into the feeld for to bring meat to the reapers. But the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Lord said vnto Abacuck. Go carry the meat that thou hast vnto Daniel, which is in the Lyons den, and the Angel of the Lorde tooke him by the haire of his head, &amp; through a mightie winde set him in Babilon vpon the
<pb facs="tcp:16559:15"/> den. And Abacuck cried saying: O Daniell thou seruant of God, haue, take the breakefast that God hath sent thee. And Daniel said: O God, hast thou thought vpon mee? Well thou neuer failest them that looue thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God hath fed his <hi>Daniels, Luther zuin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glius, Caluin,</hi> and infinite such others in the Lions den of persecution and trouble he hath sent vnto them many <hi>Abacucks</hi> to bring to them the potage and comforte of God his goodnes prepared for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and worldlings, for God neuer fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth those that looue him. Thoughe the Water and Manna of the Gospell bée not so plentifull. Though the meale and Oyle of Religion be not so abundant.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Daniels</hi> and preachers be not so wel fed and comforted in the wildernes of this world, as good and zelous men doo wish, let them be content and take pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and relye vpon this. God must féede his Church in the wildernes, a thousand, two hundred and thrée score daies. Let them remēber the answere that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the soules of those which were kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the testimony which they had, which cried with a loud voice, and saide:
<pb facs="tcp:16559:16"/>
                  <hi>How long Lord thou holy &amp; true wil it be ere thou reuenge the bloud of thy Saintes vppon those that dwel vpon the earth?</hi> &amp; they were bidden to be quiet a while, vntill the nū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of their fellow seruantes were full, which must be killed as they be.</p>
               <p>God hath a number of children that must be killed, and a number of daies in the which his children must beare his Crosse &amp; féede in the wildernes of this worlde: &amp; til the number both of the Children and daies be ful: the godly neither can haue or shal haue their ful of the heauēly Mā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and bread of the blessed meale &amp; oyle of sincere religion, which they so greatly desire: but so soone as the number of the saints and daies be ful, so soone shall they be made pillers in the church of god, and haue their ioies perfected God defend vs against the malice of sathan, and send vs his profitable rod of discipline, &amp; féede vs by his prouidence in this wildernes one thousand two hundred &amp; 3 score dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third part.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:16"/>
               <p>THe third general point, <hi>is the victory of the Church.</hi> The first particular lesson of that is the warfare. The life of man vpon earth is a warfare: and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon<note place="margin">Iob. 7. 1.</note> we call the Churche of God vppon earth, the Church militant, the fightyng and warfaring Church. In war we first<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 17.</note> looke to the manner of the fight, which is here of the spirit and of the flesh, for the flesh fighteth againste the spirit and the spirit against the flesh.</p>
               <p>These two doo contrary one to the other. The workes of the flesh are manifeste,<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 19.</note> which are these, fornication, vncleannes, incontinency, Idolatry, witchcraft, mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, contention, enuy, heresies, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, gluttony and such like. The fruites of the spirit be ioy, peace, patience, libera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie, long suffering, mildnes, faith, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destie, continency and chastitie.</p>
               <p>Next we looke vnto the captaines, and the first captaine in this war is <hi>Michaell</hi> the strong and mightie, the Lyon of the tribe of <hi>Iudah, Emanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l,</hi> the great coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, the prince of peace, the aduocate of<note place="margin">Apo. 5. 5. Ma.. 1. 13. Esa. 9. 6. 1. Ioh. 2. 1.</note> the faithful, the Angel of the testament, the head of the Church, the Conquerer of
<pb facs="tcp:16559:17"/> death hel &amp; sin. The Iudge of the quicke<note place="margin">Mala 3 1. Col. 1. 18. Act. 1. 42.</note> and the dead Christ Iesus, God eternal, God almightie. The Captaine of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther armie, is the great red Dragon, the old Serpent, the deceiuer of the whole<note place="margin">Apo. 12. 10 Eph. 6. 12.</note> world, the accuser of our brethrē day and night, the worldly ruler, the gouernour of darkenes in this world, which is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil and Sathan.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Michaels</hi> souldiers be the ministers of<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 4.</note> Christ, the elect, the Children of light, the blessed of the Father. The Dragons Souldiers, be the ministers of Sathan, the wicked, the Children of darkenes, the curssed.</p>
               <p>The armoure of the Christian Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, is the girdle of trueth, the brestplate of righteousnes, the shooes of peace, the shéeld of Faith, the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God. The Helmet of saluation, the darts of Praier, fasting and almes. Then the armour of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary souldiers must needs be, the Girdle of Falshood, the brestplate of Iniury, the shooes of discord, the sheeld of infidelitie, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sword of the flesh, which is the doctrine &amp; wisedome of man, the helmet of mistrust
<pb facs="tcp:16559:17"/> the darts of deuoutlesnesse, epicurisme, and vnmercifulnesse. It is a good rule in Logick, that of contraries there is the same knowledge, as white and blacke, good and bad. Then he that shall knowe the bad weapons, shall also knowe the good, which I will brieflie run ouer.</p>
               <p>The first is, the Girdle of Falsehood, which containeth all lying, sophistrie, and hipocrisie. So the children of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse gird themselues, first with false spéeches, false rumours, false surmises, sclanderous bookes, and infamous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, false othes, protestations and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crations, false accusers, and false witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses.</p>
               <p>Next, with Sophistrie and doubling, vsing words and sentences of double sence, to the contrarie of the meaning, ioining words togither that are disioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning▪ or disioining words and sentences which should be red whole: by wrong pointing and pronouncing, by changing the substance into the accident, or the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident into the substance, making the cause the not cause: or the not cause the cause, reporting things done or spoken
<pb facs="tcp:16559:18"/> simply, which be done or spoken in part. That is, in respect of some time, or some place, or some person, or to alledge things done or spoken in part, to be done simply, in telling of a déed, to leaue out the principall matters, and to vtter the rest as a full troth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly with hipocrisie and dissimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in pretending loue of Religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, friendship and faith, &amp; vnder the colour of those to hide superstition, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutlesnes, guile and vntroth. Examples of these in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world there be too many, but I will by a few giue you to ame at the rest: and for these false spéeches &amp; sclande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous reports, I will leaue you to the cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon tables, where either at dinner or at supper, you may heare too manie after they are warme with wine. There is nothing more necessarie now adaies, then some good order against table talke.</p>
               <p>Mens tungs now be so frée &amp; so licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, that they will spare none, not Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, not Iudge, not Shirif, not Maior, not Preacher, not Bishop, not gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, not noble man, not Councellor, not Prince. And surely this libertie is as it
<pb facs="tcp:16559:18"/> were the séed and spring of rebellion: for when they haue reuealed euery state their fill: then they begin to agrée togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to publish infamous bookes, to set robberies, rebellions, and insurrections, and to frame new common wealthes.</p>
               <p>Sophisters were wont to be only in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> scholes, but now they be euery where. The farmer and grasier can play the so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phister, in hiding in their corne and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell till the price be raised. The artificer can play the Sophister, in making his wares shew better then they be. Petifog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers at the law can play the sophisters, in setting a good face, and applying good words to a bad matter, in pretending truth &amp; iustice, when they séeke to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw truth &amp; iustice. Officers can play the sophisters, and pretend Iustice, and yet séeke gaine and luker. In Religion, men can play the sophisters, and talke of the catholicke church, when they meane the church of Roome. And talke of good works: when they meane dead works. Talke of faith and conscience: when they meane opinion and fancie. Men can talke of the reformation of the Church:
<pb facs="tcp:16559:19"/> and meane the spoile of the goods and lands of the Church. All these be Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and gird themselues with falshood.</p>
               <p>The next is the brestplate of iniurie, which containeth wrongfull déeds, whē by authoritie and might, mens goods bée taken away or holden back. And to leaue the common wrongs, there be sproong vp new kinds much to be bewailed. The one be sea théeues, suche as lie in the straights and corners of the fea, and take other mens goodes from them by force, and make them often times water spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels, or send them to féed Haddocks, as they call it. And among the greatest of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders in this kind, some Englishmen be thought to be. There will lie togither either men of diuers nacions, or such as can speake diuers languages, so that whatsoeuer nation the Merchant be of, the pirats will be of another and of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther language. Poore men lose their liues, and true men their goodes. Before God I speake it, I thinke the sea be curs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed for these murthers and robberies. And I am sure God will curse this land, for nurssing and fostering them without
<pb facs="tcp:16559:19"/> repentance and iustice done vpon the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders. Let men pretend what they will, God is the God of iustice. They giue them this od name or that. If they were Turkes, or Iewes, or Infidels, wrong ought not to be done to them. Nay rather we ought to deale so iustlie, and so vprightlie with them, that they séeing our good works, might be won to honour our God, &amp; professe our Gospell.</p>
               <p>Another be land théeues, such as get fatherlesse childrens goodes into theyr hands, and either defraude them of the whole, or else of the greater part. And if they will not be content with a little péece, do driue them to the lawe, and so make them spend more then their lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or portions commeth to, before they obtaine it.</p>
               <p>A third of such as be in the commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the peace, or for the Subsidies, or for musters, which vse those commissions to gaine by. Such as will bring them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and passe at Sises and Sessions in Iewries, as they would haue them, shall be little or nothing in the subsidies booke: they shall be charged with little or
<pb facs="tcp:16559:20"/> no armour: shall not be appointed to the warres, nor looked to in the musters. But such as can not, or will not reward priuatly, nor pin their consciences to his sléeue, or his stéeue: they pay for all. So that the payments now adaies in manie places, rest vpon the thrée pound men, or foure pound men, or fiue pound men: which God knoweth néeds more to haue giuen them then to pay oftentimes. And the great rich men, which be worth a thousand, fiue-thousand, nay ten thousand pounds, scape for ten pounds, twentie, thirtie, fortie, fiftie pounds at the most. The next point of Armour, be the shooes of discord, of enuie, hatred and malice, wherewith the souldiers of darkenes be shod, whereof our daies are too full, and the daies whereof it was said, <hi>Frigebit charitas muliorum.</hi> The loue of manie<note place="margin">Matth. 24. 12.</note> shall warkey cold. And yet we are full of one kind of charitie: but it is but a blind charitie, and vncharitable charity. This must néeds be a point of charitie to further your neighbour to heauen. And surely there be many that had leuer haue their neighbour go to heauen rather then
<pb facs="tcp:16559:20"/> themselues. For one good helpe to heauē it is, for a man to be told his faults. And many be ready not only to tell, but to write and print their neighbours faults: their coldnesse in religion, their slacke faith, their want of hospitalitie, their doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this euill déed and that euill déede, they leaue nothing foorth, nay they will ad and deuise. This is a kind of charitie, for it maketh good Christians more ware and circumspect in their déedes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them call to remēbrance, whether they haue offended God or their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in that sort. But this is vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble charitie, for it groweth not of hate of vice, or loue of vertue: but of enuy, malice and cōtention, to deface their neighbour.</p>
               <p>The next point of armour is the shéeld of infidelitie, whereof I am verie loth to speake, &amp; loth to suppose that any should be faultie. I trust there bée none that doubt either of God or of the Diuell, or of heauen or of hell, or of the resurrection of the dead, or of the life to come. Though some liue so, and speake so, as they gyue great occasion to many to suspect that they looke for no life after this life.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:21"/>
               <p>The Papists were wont to say, that this religion would bring in infidelitie, but most falsely and most vntruly: mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, what want of discipline hath done and may do, that is another point. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath there beene, nor is, nor can bée any fault in the religion, for it is the sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Religion that Christ Iesus left to his Church. But surely the remisnes of Magistrates either hath done or may doo much harme. Many there be that make little account of common praier, and as little of the word or of the Sacraments. Not surely, bicause they want zeale and religion altogither, but either they beare themselues of the losenesse of the time, or of the countenance of some great persons vpon whome they depend. In that case there be diuers partlie irreligious, and partlie Papists and spies to, that few or none dare or may controll them, without greater danger to the controller, then to the controlled. These talke their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of Christian preachers and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and iest at common praier and at Sermons, and at euery good thing. But this is the fault of man and time, not the
<pb facs="tcp:16559:21"/> fault of▪ Religion. And therefore it is to be said, <hi>Qui sordescit sordescat adhuc,</hi> they<note place="margin">Apoc. 22. verse. 81.</note> that will néeds bée naught, let them bée naught.</p>
               <p>Men may not cut downe Vines, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause▪ bad men be drunken with wine. Neither take away mariage bicause bad men breake wedlocke. Neither take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the law, bicause bad petifoggers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buse the lawe to quarrell and trouble poore men. Neither may we take away the word of God and the Sacraments bicause bad men abuse them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne them to their owne destruction. We preach Christ crucified, to the Iews<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. verse. 25.</note> a stumbling blocke, to the Gentiles foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnesse. But to those that be called both of the Iewes and Gréekes, Christ the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God, and the wisedome of God. For the word of the crosse is foolishnesse<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. verse. 18.</note> to them that perish: but to those that bée saued it is the power of God. Preachers be the swéet sauour vnto God, both in<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2. verse. 15.</note> those that be saued and in those that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, to the one the sauour of death vnto death, and to the other the sauour of life vnto life.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:22"/>
               <p>The next point of this armour is, the sword of the flesh, which is the doctrine of man and the wisedome of man. It is ingraffed in the corrupt nature of man to loue the works of his owne hands, to séeke to be as wise as God. God appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Noah</hi> to make an Arke to saue▪ him<note place="margin">Gen. 6. 14 Gen. 11. 4</note> &amp; his. And <hi>Nimbrod</hi> would néeds build a tower to re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h to heauen. The Angell of God appointed <hi>Lot</hi> to go to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note place="margin">Gen. 19. verse. 17. Gen. 19. verse. 20.</note> to saue himselfe: and he néedes would go to <hi>Soar,</hi> where he fell into in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cest. God made the children of <hi>Israel</hi> two tables of stone: and they made thēselues<note place="margin">Exo. 31. 18 Exo. 32. 4. Iud. 8. 27. Iud. 11. 39. 1. Sam. 15 verse. 9.</note> two golden calues. <hi>Gedeon</hi> would néeds make himselfe an Ephod: and <hi>Iephthah</hi> sacrifice his daughter, and <hi>Saule</hi> saue the faire oxen and shéepe to sacrifice.</p>
               <p>God hath appointed his <hi>Noahs,</hi> the arke faith in the death and merits of Christ to be saued by. But the <hi>Nimbrodes</hi> of this world, build towers of the merits of saints, of their owne merits, of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinesse of the worke, and the worthines of the worker, of <hi>Congruum</hi> &amp; <hi>Condignum,</hi> of supererogation and ceremonies, and rites and outward shewes, and thinke
<pb facs="tcp:16559:22"/> that these towers will reach vp to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. But they build <hi>Babel</hi> and confusion. <hi>There is no other name giuen vnder heauen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4. 12.</note>
                  <hi>whereby we may be saued, but only in the name of Christ Iesus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The word of God appointed all <hi>Lots</hi> to run out of <hi>Sodome</hi> of darkenes &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, to the mountaine <hi>Moses,</hi> to the mountains the Prophets, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mountains the Euangelists, &amp; the scriptures of God in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> which life is. But blind zealous <hi>Lots</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 39.</note> like not y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> mountains liked of a few, and frequēted of a few. But they desire to go to the citie &amp; <hi>Segor,</hi> they must haue a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible church and a visible hed, &amp; al things visible. God gaue to his primatiue church the old Testament and the new, the law and the Gospell. But the blinde zealous <hi>Israelites</hi> afterwards made vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues the golden calues of gallant copes, &amp; crosses, and Ceremonies, and Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticks and Schoolemen, and Sophisters, and Doctors, and Legends, and Glosers. Gedeons will haue their owne deuises, their owne fancies. The publique order of praier cannot please them, the commō order of ministration of Sacraments
<pb facs="tcp:16559:23"/> can not content them. But euery <hi>Gede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> must haue his owne Ephod. Euerie one his owne maner and forme, except he first find that way, it is not worth a strawe. <hi>Iephtha</hi> will serue God after his owne fancie, or hee will sacrifice his daughter. Superstitious <hi>Iephthas</hi> sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice both their sonnes and their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and themselues: they destroy all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a blind zeale, which they haue vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and professed, and their forefathers before them. They will not learne with good king <hi>Dauid</hi> to teach their children<note place="margin">Psa. 78. 8.</note> the law of God, that they should not bee as their forefathers were, a faithles and stubborne generation, a generation that set not their harts aright.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saules</hi> must sacrifice faire shéepe and faire oxen, they must haue euery thing goodly and gay to the eye, and thinke whatsoeuer séemeth goodly and gaie in their owne eies: must néedes séeme so in Gods eie, although he hath taught the contrarie.</p>
               <p>The next point of this armour is the helmet of mistrust. The children of <hi>Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> fondlie armed themselues with this
<pb facs="tcp:16559:23"/> helmet of mistrust, when they sayd vnto <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron. <hi>Would to God we had dyed by the hands of Pharao in the land of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, when we sate by the pots of flesh, and had bread inough. Why haue you brought vs into the wildernesse, to kill all the people with hunger?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>And they arme themselues with the helmet of mistrust, which say, now haue we the fleshpots of peace, and the bread of wealth, and all things as we would. What should we make any stur, or vse discipline against the stubborne? so may we raise trouble, and heape coales vpon our owne heads. The word of God is to be preached, and the children of <hi>Israell</hi> must be brought out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline is to be ministred. And for the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell we should rely vpon the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and maiestie of God.</p>
               <p>The children of <hi>Israell</hi> againe armed themselues with this helmet of mistrust, saying: <hi>Would to God we might die, and that God would not bring vs into this land, least</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 14. verse. 2.</note>
                  <hi>we should die with the sword, and our wiues and our children be led away captiues, is it not better to returne into Egipt?</hi> And they
<pb facs="tcp:16559:24"/> againe arme themselues with the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of mistrust, which say, we will not venture too far, we will not shew our selues too zealous, least we héereafter die with the sword, and our wiues and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren loose our lands and goods. It is good for vs for to make faire weather before hand, that if occasion serue, we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into <hi>Egypt.</hi> This gracelesse mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strust, and this causelesse mistrust, is the greatest hinderance of religion and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue now adaies. For there be a great sort that will not bind and tie themselues to religion and the prouidence of God: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they feare y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> mooneshine in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; doubt that that may come, which either will neuer come, or it is like i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that they shall neuer liue to sée it come. Or if our sinnes be so great that God will send it, their mistrust is but lost, it will neuer serue their turnes. Let them looke to the Admirall <hi>Herne</hi> &amp; <hi>Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,</hi> and others that haue trusted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, and behold their owne destinie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rasin</hi> of <hi>Siria,</hi> and <hi>Pecath</hi> the sonne of<note place="margin">2. Reg. 16. verse. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Romelia,</hi> went to Ierusalem to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it. And assoone as <hi>Ahas</hi> and hys
<pb facs="tcp:16559:24"/> people heard thereof, they put on the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met of mistrust, and their harts quaked as the leaues of a trée shooke with the wind. But God by his Prophet <hi>Esay</hi> said vnto them. Feare not, nor be faint har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for these two tailes, and for these two smoking firebrands. If you beléeue not: it commeth of this, that you are vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God.</p>
               <p>And they arme themselues with the helmet of mistrust, whose harts tremble at the comming of <hi>Rasin</hi> and <hi>Pecath,</hi> nay vpon the report of their comming. Whē God doth plainelie showe that they bée but two tailes, two smoking firebrands, two that cannot helpe themselues, nay that néed helpe themselueo. Two whose fathers being x. times more mightie then they, could not ouerthrow the Gospell in their own countries: whosoeuer doth not beléeue this, it commeth of this, that they doo not depend vpon Gods maiestie and prouidence, but be vnfaithfull to God.</p>
               <p>The last point of this armoure be the darts of deuoutlesnes, vnmercifulnes &amp; epicurisme, which flie abrode in euerie place, for few or none there be that serue
<pb facs="tcp:16559:25"/> God deuoutlie. Some there be that come to common praier, and heare Sermons as it were for a fashion. Good Lord, what deuotion was there and zeale in the children of darkenesse? They would go a foote many an hundred miles to a dum Image. They would rise by mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and tarrie all the morning in the Church cold and hungrie, to heare that that they vnderstood not, they gaue away their goods and their lands to cloth Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, they would eate nothing but bread and water full many a time, and spare from their owne bellie to bestowe it as their zeale led them. I leaue them to God, I hope the best.</p>
               <p>But we that haue the light of the Gospell, that knowe true religion and true faith and true praier, and true almes, haue little deuotion, either to fast or to doo the works of true mercie.</p>
               <p>We will scarce rise at seuen a clocke, nay▪ at nine a clocke to heare the word of God, and to serue God, we will not go a mile, nay we will scarce go out of our chambers and houses to heare Christ preached, and to honour God in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.
<pb facs="tcp:16559:25"/> Neuer so little businesse stai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs from sermons and praier.</p>
               <p>We thinke we may pray when we list, but we are to to much deceiued. For faithfull praier is the gift of God, and the gifts of God haue their times. And be well likened to the little boy, which the Poets call <hi>Occasion,</hi> which is pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a bald head, sauing that he had in his forehead a little locke of haire and with wings, and a sythe in his hand, meaning that he did flie apace, and cut away all things with him: meaning that if a man did not take hold of the little locke when it was before him: he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld not take hold of the bald part.</p>
               <p>The daies were when manie of vs would haue giuen all the goods we had and the lands to, that we might without bodely danger haue serued God in such sort as now we may. And yet we will not take hold of the little locke of grace when we may, but féed our selues with securitie and carelesnesse, and vaine fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. We do not onlie not works of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in maintaining preachers and relée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the poore: but our most studie is to
<pb facs="tcp:16559:26"/> take away that little that is left to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and to pull downe Hospitalles, or to take away the lands, or kéepe away the rents from the poore. Abstinence to make our bodies the more fit to serue God, is so far from vs, as many mens chiefe studie is to deuise new pleasures and new deuises to delight the carcasses too much pampered.</p>
               <p>The next particular lesson, is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow of the Dragon and his souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, they preuailed not, they were cast downe to the ground, they were vtterlie ouerthrowen. <hi>Death is swallowed vp in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 55.</note>
                  <hi>victorie, death where is thy sting? hell where is thy victorie? The sting of death is sin, and the strength of sin is the law, but thanks be vnto God which hath giuen vnto vs▪ victorie tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our Lord Iesus Christ. All that is borne of God ouercommeth the world, and this is the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1. 4.</note>
                  <hi>victorie that ouercommeth the world euen our faith. Who is he that ouercommeth the world, but he that beleeueth that Iesus is the sonne of God▪</hi> So neither the captaines nor souldiers can stand or preuaile. And no maruell, for their armour is of Cheuerel lether, &amp; the nature of Cheuerel lether is,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:26"/> that if a man take it by the sides &amp; pull it in breadth, he may make a little point as brode as both his hands. If he take it by the ends &amp; pull it in length, he may make it as small as a thréed. Most men now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies haue Cheuerel consciences, if the matter touch their owne profit or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure: they make their consciences wide inough, &amp; large inough. If it touch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans profit, they make them as small as a thréed. Much like as the report of a Lawyer or some other, to whome a man came &amp; said. Sir my cattell haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroied your corne, what is to be done in the matter▪ Marrie (quoth he) you must pay me for my corne: Nay (quoth the foll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low) my toong slipt, it is your cattell haue destroied my corne. That altereth the case (quoth he) we will talke of that more another time. This Cheuerel conscience is brode inough to looke to his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, but narrow inough to looke to his neighbours profit. The world is full of Cheuerel cōsciences, &amp; ful of <hi>Dionisians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionisius</hi> came into a temple where Images were clothed with golden cotes, and siluerne cotes. And <hi>Dionisius</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16559:27"/> tooke pitie on them and said, these golden and siluerne cotes be to heauie for som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and to cold for winter, and therefore for pitie sake he tooke away their golden and siluerne cotes, and gaue them cotes of linsey wolsey, for said he, that is good and warme for winter, and good and light for sommer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dionisius</hi> Cheuerel conscience and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is too common. What (say they) should these Preachers doo with Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships and manours and tithes. They hinder them from their bookes and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. It were better for them to haue a pension quietlie paid them, and then they might go quietlie to their bookes and to their preaching. The <hi>Dionisians</hi> take away their golden gotes and siluer cotes, and giue them linsey wolsey cotes, for they be good and warme for winter, and good and light for sommer.</p>
               <p>Rich men can say to poore men, or such as be behind hand, what should you doo with such an hold, or with such a greate occupying? you can not stocke it, sell it me and I will helpe you to a lesse and money to stocke it. <hi>Dionisians</hi> take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away
<pb facs="tcp:16559:27"/> their golden cotes, and giue them linsey wolsey, bicause it is warme and light. Such as haue store of money, can say to others, you haue such a little péece of land, you are in debt. It doth you little good or none, I will let you haue so much money vpon the morgage or sale of your land. And you may furnish your selfe and your houshold and prouide to liue vpon that, first they get away his golden cote and after his linsey wolsey, for the vse of his money in time doth eate vp both his land and his stocke, and bring him to our Ladies bands, and teach him to sing by beggerie.</p>
               <p>And héere may the bad well learne a good lesson, to cast away the girdle of fals<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and the brestplate of wrong, and all other their bad armour, for good they can doo them none, and hurt they shall doo themselues much. They that trust in those, build vppon the sand, when the wind of Gods truth shall blowe: their buildings shall be ouerthrowne. Truth is like a cole of fire, which couered with ashes, séemeth quite out, but when the bellowes hath blowen the ashes away,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:28"/> the cole is brighter than it was before. So the ashes of malice and craft may hinder the cole of truth for a while, but so soone as the bellewes of Gods spirit shall blowe vpon the ashes, the ashes will flie awaie, and truth will appeare more brighter then before.</p>
               <p>The ashes of craft and malice did hide the innocencie of <hi>Ioseph,</hi> whose féete they<note place="margin">Gen. 39. 20.</note> hurt in the Stocks, the iron entred into his soule. The bellowes of Gods truth blew abrode the ashes, the time came, that his cause was knowne, the King sent and deliuered him, he made him Lord of his house, and ruler of all his sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. So he did shine more bright then euer before.</p>
               <p>The ashes of craft and malice did hide for a while the innocencie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and cast him into the Lions den. But the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of Gods spirit blew away the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes, and the angell of God shut the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mouthes that they might not hurt him. And the King fetched <hi>Daniel</hi> out of the den, and he did shine brighter then before.</p>
               <p>The malice and craft of the noughty,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:28"/> may bring and do bring <hi>Iosephs</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> into much trouble. But Gods spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit doth blowe and shall blowe away all their malice and craft, and make their innocencie brighter then before. Well<note place="margin">Psal. 62. 10</note> said good King <hi>Dauid. <hi>Trust not in wrong and craft, for craft and wrong are pitfalles to take them in, that dig them.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>The inhabitants of <hi>Gibeon</hi> thought<note place="margin">Iosu. 9. 4.</note> they wrought wisely, who made them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>selues Ambassadours, and tooke to them victuals and bottels, old and rent, and torne, and old clouted shooes vpon their feet, and their raiment was old, and all their prouision of bread was dried vp and hored. And they came vnto <hi>Iosuah</hi> into the hoste, and said vnto him and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the men of <hi>Israel. <hi>We be come from a far countrie, this our foode of bread we tooke with vs out of our houses hote, the day we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to come to you. But now behold it is dried vp and hore, and these bottels of wine which we filled were new and see they be rent. And these our garments and shooes are worne for verie oldnesse, by reason of the exceeding long iorney</hi>
                  </hi> But within thrée daies after they were found to dwell hard by.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:29"/>
               <p>The fautors of the Romish Church, tell of their excéeding long iorney, and antiquitie of fiftéene hundred yeares and great continuance. But <hi>Iosuah</hi> hath found, and God hath showed that they dwell hard by. That their doctrine and religion is new, their greatest points of their doctrine, transubstantiation, and the Bishops primacie ouer the councell, not holden foure hundred yeares ago. And as for their horie bread of inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints, their sowre wine of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, their broken bottles of sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing for the quicke and the dead, their clouted shooes of pilgrimages, pardons, palmes, ashes, holy bread, holy water, and infinite such like, they were old and venued, and hory and rotten, euen when they tooke them first from home, as groū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not so much as of one sentence or president of canonicall scripture: yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing méere dreames and deuises of the Poets. As Purgatorie, in the sixt booke of <hi>Virgilles Aenaeidos.</hi> Inuocation of Saints in <hi>Ouid de tristibus.</hi> Holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the first booke of <hi>Ouids Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phosis,</hi> and so foorth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haman</hi> thought he had wrought wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Hest. 3. 10</note> against <hi>Mardocheus,</hi> when he had gotten a bill signed, by the King for his death. But <hi>Haman</hi> fell into the pit that he digged for <hi>Mardocheus,</hi> and was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne himselfe.</p>
               <p>Proude <hi>Hamans,</hi> ambicious <hi>Hamans,</hi> craftie and malicious <hi>Hamans,</hi> may dig pits, and doo dig pits, for poore and simple well meaning <hi>Mardocheus,</hi> but they fall into the pits themselues, and are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen. For the Dragon and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels may fight and doo fight, but they can not stand nor preuaile, but are cast down to the ground.</p>
               <p>The next lesson containeth the meanes by the which they ouercame. The first meane is the bloud of the Lamb, the cause efficient and working this victorie. We are not bought with corruptible gold and siluer, but with the bloud of the<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. verse. 18.</note> vnspotted Lamb Christ Iesus. If gold or siluer could haue ransomed vs, or if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing that could haue béene bought for siluer or gold, could saue and iustifie vs, then easie were the way to heauen for rich men. For it were but an easie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:16559:30"/> for him that hath ten thousand poūds, to bestowe one hundred. For him that may spend an hundred pounds by the yeare, to bestowe ten pounds by the yéere to come to heauen thereby.</p>
               <p>But our maister Christ telleth vs that the way to heauen for rich men is too too<note place="margin">Matth. 26. verse. 39.</note> hard. And therefore they be enemies to the death and crosse of Christ, that deuise any other cause of saluation, then the blood of the Lamb. If all the powers and vertues of all the creatures in heauen and earth and vnder the earth, had béene able to haue satisfied the wrath of God, the sonne of God should neuer haue died, for that cup should haue passed from him,<note place="margin">Matth. 26. verse. 39.</note> if it had béene possible.</p>
               <p>The second meane was the word of their testimonie, their beléefe in hart and confession▪ in mouth of Christes merits. For euen as the medicine, be it neuer so good, doth not help the patient, except he take the medicine and apply it to his gréefe: so the blood of the Lamb, though it be the most soueraine medicine in the world, yet can it not helpe the sicke soule except it be taken by the mouth of faith,<note place="margin">Act. 15. 9.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16559:30"/> and applied to the comfort of the soule. <hi>The harts be made cleane▪ by faith.</hi> Faith is that hand that taketh hold of the grace and mercie of God in the blood of the Lamb, and lodgeth the same in the hart of man▪ which being so lodged, doth wash the hart, and expulse all the filth of sinne. The beginning and the founda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion of<note place="margin">Cicil. in Iohn. li. 2. cap. 52.</note> our holinesse and righteousnes is Christ; by faith and not otherwise, for by that meane Christ doth dwell in vs. This is<note place="margin">Fulgē▪ ad memim. lib. 1.</note> the order of Gods redemption and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding man, that now ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied doth beléeue that, which to be glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he shall receiue.</p>
               <p>The third meane is the not louing of their liues vnto death. Their constancie in faith, in loue, in pitie, in truth, in the patience and kingdome of Christ. For of the good trée of grace planted in the hart by the hand of faith, must néedes spring foorth the fruites of constancie and patience, and other good workes. And these exclusiue or barring words (onlie faith, faith alone, faith without works) doo not exclude and barre good workes from a man iustified, but exclude and
<pb facs="tcp:16559:31"/> bar good works to be only fruts and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of iustification, and not causes.</p>
               <p>And it is necessary to consider the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course of the graces of God in man iusti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. The principall cause is the grace and mercie of God in Christ, the hand or instrument by the which that grace is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold of, and applied to the health of man, is faith in the death and merits of Christ.</p>
               <p>The third be good works, the fruites and tokens of grace and faith, not the causes. As it is said to the woman in the Gospell. Many sinnes are forgiuen hir,<note place="margin">Luke. 7. verse. 47.</note> bicause she loued much. Hir loue is not set downe as the cause that wrought the forgiuenesse of hir sinnes: but as the frute, token and effect. For hir sinnes were not forgiuen hir bicause she loued Christ much. But she loued Christ much bicause he had forgiuen hir many sinnes. And this doth Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> more plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie set foorth in his first Epistle. <hi>By this we</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3. verse. 14.</note>
                  <hi>knowe that we are translated from death to life, bicause we loue the brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The loue of our brethren is a tokē vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs that God hath loued vs and saued
<pb facs="tcp:16559:31"/> vs. For none can loue his brother except God hath first loued him. And thus you sée how the Saints of God get the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and saluation by the blood of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> Lamb, as the cause: by faith, as the instrument, by constancie, and patience, &amp; good works as the effects. And all these be the bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings of God, concurring in men iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ouerthrowing their enemies.</p>
               <p>The last particular lesson is the song of the victorie. The Saints vpon this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie sing this song: <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w is made saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and strength, and the kingdome of our God, and the power of his Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And againe this song. <hi>Saluation be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apo. 7. 10.</note>
                  <hi>to him that sitteth vpon the seate of our God and to the Lamb.</hi> And thirdlie this song. <hi>Blessing and glorie, and wisedome, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apo. 7. 12.</note>
                  <hi>thanks, and honour, and power, and might, be vnto our God for euermore. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When God had ouerthrowen <hi>Pharao</hi> and his hoste in the red sea. Then <hi>Moses</hi> sang this song. <hi>The Lord hath triumphed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 15. 1.</note>
                  <hi>gloriouslie, the horse and him that rode vpon him hath he ouerthrowne in the Sea. The Lord is my strength and praise, and he is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my saluation. He is my God, and I will
<pb facs="tcp:16559:32"/> glorifie him, my fathers God, and I will exalt him▪</hi> God hath cast downe the altu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of our breethren, and the oppressour of our bréethren. God hath cast to the ground the dragon of hell. God hath drowned <hi>Pharao</hi> of Roome and all his horsemen in the sea. God hath set vs frée from hell and Rome, superstition and vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>There is no nation vnder the heauen that hath better cause to praise God, then this of <hi>England.</hi> For remember first that God hath blessed vs with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> health, and wealth, and peace, and quietnes, whereas all nations round about vs, haue béene long troubled: Where they haue had sicknes we haue had none to speake of. Where they haue had hunger &amp; dearth, we haue had plentie and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, not only for our selues, but for a great many besides. We haue had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and vnitie: where they be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally vexed with ciuill warres, neighbour against neighbour, kinsman against kinsman, brother against brother, father against his sonne, the wife against hir husband, the sonne against his mother, y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> seruant against his maister, contrarie
<pb facs="tcp:16559:32"/> to all the principles of fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, nature, and reason▪ Thinke that you sée with your eies some starued with hunger, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s murdred in their beds, some slain in their féeld, some hanged, some drowned, some quartered, euery one looking euery houre for death▪ Churches burned, houses spoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, childrens braines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out, ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and matrons defloured. And then, then you will thinke how great a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of God this ciuill concord is.</p>
               <p>Go a little further, and consider what a gracious &amp; mercifull Prince God hath set ouer vs, vnder whome euerie one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioieth his goods, his lands, his wife, his children, and hath and may haue the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> law, wheras you may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that men were put to death without law, their goods taken from them contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to all law. A word hastely spoken, or rather plainely mistaken, was present death. Their wiues and their children cast out of the dores a begging. If yong men aske of their old men, they shall not find it in the memorie of the oldest men▪ so manie yeares frée from paiments and contributions, as haue béene in
<pb facs="tcp:16559:33"/> this our most gratious soueraines time.</p>
               <p>God hath giuen to this land, so manie graue, and wise, and godly Councellors, and Nobles, and gentlemen, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, &amp; of all other sorts as neither this land, nor any other haue euer or seldome séene before. Euen little children can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; more perfectly declare y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> principles of religiō and faith: then those that were reckoned great men &amp; pillers of y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> church an hundred yeares ago. Ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides that, God hath lent vnto vs his holy and blessed word in our natiue tong, and his holy Sacraments in such sort as Christ deliuered vnto his Apostles, and his Apostles vnto his Church, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test treasures y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> can happen to any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian. And for the quiet enioying wherof, you your selues would once haue giuen all the good and lands in the world, if you had had them. And yet if you cōtinue still true christian merchants, you will giue all that euer you haue for these pearles.</p>
               <p>These so great benefits of God should<note place="margin">Math. 13. verse. 45.</note> mooue vs with the Saints, with <hi>Moses,</hi> with all the holy ones, to praise God and blesse his holie name. To bée thankefull
<pb facs="tcp:16559:33"/> to God who hath delt so wonderfully for vs, and so graciously. But we lothe the heauenly Manna, we be weary of our owne ease and good, and spend our daies in sclandring, backebiting, quarreling, wringing, and wronging one of another. We leaue the substance of religion and let that sléepe, and vexe and trouble our selues about the accidents and beggerly elements of the world. The feare of God &amp; the loue of our neighbour is too to cold, Infidelitie and vncharitablenesse beare the bel.</p>
               <p>Repent England repent, repent London repent, repent old and yong, rich &amp; poore, for he hath whet his sword, and bent hys bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, and prepared in it the arrowes of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wash you and make you cleane, put away your euill intents out of his sight. Leaue to doe euill, learne to doe well, deliuer the oppressed, helpe the fatherlesse to his right, let the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes complaint come before you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Amend your waies &amp; councels, iudge right betwixt a man and his neighbour, oppresse not the stranger, the the fatherlesse, nor the widow, cleaue not to strange Gods and fond fancies to
<pb facs="tcp:16559:34"/> your owne destruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Turne you to the Lord your God with all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioel. 2. 12.</note>
                  <hi>your hartes with fasting, weeping, &amp; mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Rent your hartes and not your garments. Turne you vnto the Lord your God: for he is gracious and merciful, long suffering and of great compassion, and readye to pardon wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:34"/>
            <head>The second Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched at Westminster <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the</hi> Queenes <hi>Maiestie the</hi> third Sonday in Lent 1576.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Actes. 20.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="28">28. <hi>Take heede to your selues, &amp; to all the flock ouer the which the holy ghost hath made you ouerseers, to feede the churche of God, whiche hath made again with his own bloud.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="29">29. <hi>For I knowe, that assoone as I am gone, there will brust in vpon you rauening woolues not sparing the flocke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="30">30. <hi>And of your selues shal arise men spea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king crooked things to drawe Schollers after them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="31">31. <hi>And thus brethren, I commend you to God, and to the worde of his grace, whiche is able to finish his buildings, and to giue you an inheritance amongst all his blessed Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:35"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He holy Ghost by Saint <hi>Paule</hi> in this portion of Scripture doth exhort al Christian Magistrates, to see that both they them selues, and al their flocks and cures be sound in religion, vertuous in life, and continue in the same vnto the end.</p>
            <p>First because the holy Ghoste hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them authority and blessings, to this end and purpose, to féede, instruct, and go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerne the Churche and people of God. Secondlye because the Soules of men committed to their charge, be a most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious treasure, as made againe with the bloud of the Lambe of God. Thirdly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the perils and dangers that hang ouer their heads, either from the woolfe, and professed enimie or from the dissem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling brethrē: occasion them to be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>Last of all, he doth anchor them vpon God and the word of his grace, againste all perils and lets, and to all good successe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this is the sum, and now more
<pb facs="tcp:16559:35"/> particularly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Saint <hi>Paule</hi> had planted the Gospel in the churches of <hi>Asia,</hi> and was sent for by the holy ghost, to go to Roome to preach the Gospel there, before his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture he called togither the Elders of the churches. <hi>Presbuteros,</hi> y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> magistrates as well ecclesiasticall as ciuill. And to them, and by them to all Christian magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates high and lowe, that haue bin since now be or shal be to the end of the world he spake to this effect, <hi>Attendite.</hi> Take great héede to your selues, watch &amp; pray, be circumspect and careful, looke diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about you.</p>
            <p>Remembring that our maister Christ gaue much the like rule to his disciples at his departure. <hi>Take heede, watch &amp; pray</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 3. 35.</note>
               <hi>for you knowe not when the time is. Watch for you knowe not when the maister of the house will come, at euen or at midnight, at the Cock crowing, or in the dawning, lest if he come sud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>denly he should find you sleeping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you should sléepe and be idle, secure carelesse, and your maister so finde you: he woulde say cut vp these vnfruitfull
<pb facs="tcp:16559:36"/> trées, and cast them in the fire. Who is therfore a faithfull seruant &amp; wise, whom his maister hath made ruler ouer his hou sholde to giue them meate in due season. <hi>Blessed is that seruant whom his maister whē he commeth shall find so doing. Verely, I say vnto you, he shal make him ruler ouer all hys goods. But if the euill seruant shall say in his hart my maister doth defer his comming, and begin to smite his fellowes, and to eate and to drinke with the drunken, That seruants mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster will come in a day when he looketh nor for him, and in an houre that he is not ware of, &amp; will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut him of, and giue him his portion with hypocrites: there shal be weeping, &amp; gnashing of teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And consider the season<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, that it is nowe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 11.</note>
               <hi>time that you should arise from steepe. For nowe is your saluation nearer than when wee beleeued it. The night is past, the daye is at hand. Let vs therefore cast away the workes of darkenesse, and put vppon vs the armoure of light so that we walke honestly as in the day, not in gluttony and drunkennesse, neither in Chamberyng and want<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nesse, nor in strife and enuying, But put you on the Lord Ies<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Christ, and take no thought for the flesh to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l
<pb facs="tcp:16559:36"/> the lusts of it Pray alwaies with all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 18.</note>
               <hi>of praier, and supplication in the Spirit, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atch there vnto with all perseueraunce and supplication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shepeheards watche day and night. Cockes doe crowe earely and late, Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen doe till the grounde and sowe, be the wether neuer so vncertaine. And the Trumpeter must sound his trumpet he the fight neuer so fierce. And you must hée good Christian shepeheards in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Good cocks in crowing, good husband<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men in tilling, good Trumpeters in sounding your faith and Religian, at all times and seasons in the Churche of God.</p>
            <p>But you will say, what néede this to vs? Wee be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>well setled in Religion, and professe the Gospell of Christe. I know it right well, And yet haue you great néede to watche and take héede that your life be agreeable to your Doctrine. For althoughe you be iustified fréelye and fully by faith in the death and merits of Iesus Christe the Sonne of GOD: yet must you doe good workes, to shew your selues vnto y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> world, to draw others
<pb facs="tcp:16559:37"/> to the praise of God, to stop the mouths of such as would blame your Religion for your bad life. To shew your selues thāk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to that good God, that hath delt so fréely and so gratiously with you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For net such as heare the law: but suche as</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 13 Ma.. 7. 21</note>
               <hi>doe the lawe are iust before. God Not euer ye one that saith, Lord, Lord, shal enter into the kingdome of Heauen: but he that doth the wil of the father which is in heauen.</hi> Thoughe you take hold of things with your hands only, yet may you and must you walke with your féete. Though you take holde of the merits of Christ, the grounde and cause of your saluation by faith only: yet may you and must you walk in y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> pathes of holynesse and righteousnesse al y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> daies of your life. Though the fruite that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of the trée planted in a good ground, be no cause of the planting or growing of the trée: yet a good trée being planted in a good grounde will both bud and blossome and bring forth good fruits. Though good workes be no cause of the planting and growing of the grace and mercy of God, in a christian hart: yet the grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie of God planted by the hande of faith,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:37"/> will and must bring forth the buds, blos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes, and fruit of vertue and trueth.</p>
            <p>Faith is the beginning of our iustifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with God, which beléeueth in him that doth iustifie. And this faith being iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified as a roote receiuing moisture from the raine, doth fasten in the ground of the soule, &amp; when it is manured by the lawe of God, there growe boughes in it which bring forth the fruit of good workes.</p>
            <p>You cannot be straight, if your fayth be dead, if your workes be dead, if you haue no deuotion. The lack of loue is the death of faith. If you beléeue in Christe, doe the workes of Christ, that your faith may liue. Let loue shew your faith to be aliue, and your déedes declare it. Let not the earthly workes crook that which your heauenly faith maketh straight.</p>
            <p>Who is so fond, as to take vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe the name of a soldier, if he cannot handle his weapon. None can well take the name without the effect. He that will be called a Goldesmith, must woorke in gold and siluer. None can well take the name of a Carpenter, except he can hew, and square and frame and ioyne the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:16559:38"/> togither.</p>
            <p>So cannot you be called Christians, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept the works of Christians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> re in you. A Christian is the name of iustice mercy, integritie, patience, chastitie, wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, humblenesse, deuotion. Neither cā you chalenge the name if you haue none of the works. He is a Christian that in al things followeth Christ.</p>
            <p>You be Souldiers in the Campe. of Christ; and Carpenters in the house and Church of Christ. You be Christes gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smiths, therfore must you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ights with the armour of iustice and mercy; and square the Timber of Integritie and patience, and gild your soules with faith. Chasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, humblenes and deuotion. Take ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore good héede vnto your selues, that you be not only zealous and sound in Reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion, but also dutiful to your superiours, iust and true in word and déede, charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your neighbours, careful and redy to féede Christe in the hungry, to clothe<note place="margin">Ma. 25. 35.</note> Christe in the naked, to lodge Christ in the harbourlesse to comfort Christ in the comfortlesse, to reléeue. Christ in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soner, the poore widdowe▪ the straunger,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:38"/> the fatherlesse child, and in all such as lye wounde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the way of this wide world,<note place="margin">Luc. 10. 34</note> poure in the wine and oyle of good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel and reléefe, binde vp the woundes of paine and sorrow.</p>
            <p>Neither is it inough for you to begin to beléeue and doo wel, but you must also continue to thend in beléeuing and doing<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 24.</note> wel, <hi>Many run in a race, but such onely get the garland as run to the goale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you would get the garland of eternall glory: you must run in the race of saith,<note place="margin">Mat 24. 13.</note> and vertue, to the goale of death. <hi>For bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed is he that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th perseuer to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may not be like <hi>Ecebolius</hi> a so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phister of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> who in the time of the good Emperour <hi>Constantine,</hi> séemed a good Christian both for beléefe &amp; life. But in the daies of <hi>Iulianus Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata,</hi> he was a cruell persecutor And in the daies of the good Emperour <hi>Iounanus,</hi> he cast himselfe downe before the dore of the Oratory, and cryed out, <hi>Calcate me salem insipidum.</hi> Treade me downe vnsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorie salt.</p>
            <p>You may not be <hi>Ecebolians,</hi> nor chāge your faith and religion with Emperours
<pb facs="tcp:16559:39"/> kings and princes. You may not be <hi>Ece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans,</hi> or change your faith in the daies of the same princes, now hot now cold as the world goeth. You may not be <hi>Esaues</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 24. Ge. 25. 33.</note> in selling your birth right of grace, for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> potage of pleasure, nor mingle Religion and vertue with pleasure and profit. You<note place="margin">Ma. 6. 24.</note> cannot serue God and <hi>Mammon.</hi> God will either be all your God, or no part of your god. If you hold 1 aker of your state of the Lordship of <hi>Mammon,</hi> you forfait all that you hold of God. <hi>The first and grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>test commandement is. Thou shalt looue the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22 37</note>
               <hi>Lord thy God, with all thy hart, with all thy soule, with all thy might, with all thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You shoulde be <hi>Gedeons</hi> to fight the battel of the Lord valiantly in the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of this life. But you may not bée <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deons</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 8. 27.</note> in making you Ephods, of the Ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rings of the <hi>Midians,</hi> and the collers and Iewels and purple raiment, that was vp on the kings of <hi>Midian,</hi> and chaines that were about the Camels necks. Yée may not set your delight vpon the glistering and goodly pleasures of this world. You<note place="margin">4. Reg. 18. 4.</note> shoulde be <hi>Ezechiases</hi> in causing all the
<pb facs="tcp:16559:39"/> people to come to the houses of the Lord, and to offer the passeouer of praier and thankes giuing, and hearing of the word of God, receiuing the supper of the Lord: In putting away the hil Aulters, and cutting downe the groues, and breaking the brazen Serpent of error and idolatry But you may may not be <hi>Ezechiases</hi> in shewing or vsing your treasures y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> giftes and blessings that God hath beautified<note place="margin">2. Reg. 20. 13.</note> your bodies and soules with, to please ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your selues or the affections of the world. You haue laid your handes to the plough of Religion and vertue, you may<note place="margin">Luc. 9. 62.</note> not looke backe to <hi>Sodom,</hi> sin and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>The spirit said to the church of <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia. <hi>I knowe thy workes that thou art neither colde nor hot▪ I would thou were colde or hot.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 3. 15.</note>
               <hi>Therefore because thou art luke warme, and neither cold nor hot: it will come to passe that I wil cast thee out of my mouth.</hi> God liketh on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly such as be zealous, &amp; addict themselues to his Religion, and feare, and seruice. Euen as an horse being very sightly and faire, is nothing worth, except he hath a pace: euen so he that is of no Religion or
<pb facs="tcp:16559:40"/> doth halt in Religion or conuersatiō, can not stand in Gods sight.</p>
            <p>The Spirit spake vnto the Churche of <hi>Pergamus, <hi>I knowe thy workes, and where</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 2. 13.</note>
               <hi>thou dwellest, euen where Sathans throne is. And thou keepest my name and hast not deni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed my faith, euen in those daies, whē <hi>Antipas</hi> my faithfull seruaunte was slaine among you, where Sathan dwelleth. But I haue a fewe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 24. 14.</note>
               <hi>things against the, because thou hast thē there that maintaine the doctrine</hi> of Balam, <hi>which taught Balac to put a stumbling blocke before the children of Israell, that they shoulde eate of things sacrificed vnto Idols, and to commit fornication. Euen so▪ thou hast thē that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the doctrin of Nicholaitans, which thing I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It wil not be inough for you to haue bin constant. When <hi>Antipasles</hi> and faithful Martires were slaine: but you must also expell and driue from among you, the <hi>Baalamits,</hi> and supersticious, whiche put stumbling blocks before simple <hi>Israelit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and cause many to eate of the sacrifice of Idolatrye. You must put from among you the <hi>Nicolaitans</hi> and vitious persons, which defile them selues with vice and
<pb facs="tcp:16559:40"/> wic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dnes.</p>
            <p>The Sonne of God that hath eyes<note place="margin">Apo. 2. 18.</note> like a sla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of fire, and his féet like brasse (sayeth to the Churche of <hi>Thyatyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:) I knowe thy works and thy loue and seruice, &amp; faith, and thy patience, and thy deedes, and that they are more at the last, than at the first: notwithstanding I haue seene a thing against thee, that thou sufferest the woman Iesabell, which calleth hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> self a Prophetisse, to teach &amp; deceiue my seruants, to make them to commit fornicatiō, &amp; to eat meat sacrificed vnto idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fiery eyes of Gods wisdome, and the brasen féete of his Iustice doo not only looke that you should increase and go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in faith, in workes, and looue, and seruice and patience: but also to suppresse the woman <hi>Iesabel,</hi> the erronious church and people, which call themselues the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick church, and yet which teache and deceiue Gods seruants, and plucke them from true religion, and cause them to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the Idols, superstition and vani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie. But you will say, that I knowe that you be well▪ affected in religion, and well disposed in good works, and bent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the grace of God. And yet haue
<pb facs="tcp:16559:41"/> you néede to watch and take héed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the stock be so likewise.</p>
            <p>A philosopher of your owne, saith, we be not borne to our selues only: but our Country claimeth part of vs, our parents claime part of vs, our fréends claime part <hi>The Candle doth not giue light to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t selfe, but</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 15. 14.</note>
               <hi>to those that be in the house. Ye be the light of the world. Salt doth not season it self but other meats.</hi> And you must shine to the worlde, you must season and profit your brethrē.</p>
            <p>They be all partes of one mistical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. 27. Eph. 4. 24. Gen. 1. 26. 1. Pet. 1. 19. 16,</note> They be al citizens of one heauenlye <hi>Hierusalem.</hi> They be al framed after the glorious Image of the same eternal god. Al ransomed with the precious bloud of the same vnspotted Lamb Christ Iesus. All lightned and guilted, with the same holy spirit of God. You must euery one of you be <hi>Iosuahs,</hi> and sée that not only you:<note place="margin">Iosu. 24</note> but al your houses and cities, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and people serue the Lord. <hi>Ioseph</hi> opened all places where store of Corne<note place="margin">Gen, 41. 16</note> was, and solde corne to al <hi>Egyptians. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi> must teach al, release al, and do Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice to all.</p>
            <p>Christ stood in the midst of his disciples
<pb facs="tcp:16559:41"/> Christ biddeth his disciples to preach the<note place="margin">Iohn. 20. 19. Matth. 28. 19.</note> Gospell to euerie creature. And you must stand in the midst of the disciples and people, and sée euerie one taught the gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and take héed to your selues, and to all the flocke of Christ. You shall be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the rather to this carefulnesse, if you consider from whence you receiue this calling, not of your fréends, not of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie creatures, but from the holy Ghost. The holy Ghost hath made you <hi>Episco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos,</hi> ouerséers, ouerlookers, and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ouer the flocke of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is no power but of God, and the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>that be, are ordeined of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I haue said you are Gods and the children</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 82.</note>
               <hi>of the most highest.</hi> The Lord said vnto <hi>Moses. <hi>Behold, I haue made thee Pharaohs</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 1.</note>
               <hi>God</hi> Thus saith <hi>Cirus</hi> king of <hi>Persia. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord God of heauen hath giuen me</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Esd. 1. 2.</note>
               <hi>all the kingdomes of the earth.</hi> When God blessed his Church of <hi>Israel,</hi> he said thus:<note place="margin">Esd. 49. 23.</note>
               <hi>Kings shall bee thy fostering fathers, and Queenes thy nursing mothers: they shall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with their faces towards the earth, and licke vp the dust of thy feete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God hath giuen you power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:42"/> God hath made you the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the highest, and made you Gods of the world, and giuen you the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the earth, and hath made you nursses of his people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And marke well to what end.</hi> Neither to growe in riches, nor to liue in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, nor to oppresse the weaker, but to féed the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Open thy mouth for the dumb, in the cause</hi>
               <note place="margin">prou. 31. 8.</note>
               <hi>of all the children of destruction. Open thy mouth, iudge righteousnesse, and iudge the afflicted and poore.</hi> Good <hi>Iob</hi> saith: <hi>When the eare heard me, it blessed me, and when the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 29. 11.</note>
               <hi>eye sawe me, it gaue witnesse to me, for I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered the poore that cried, and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, and him that had none to helpe him. The blessing of him that was readie to perish came vpon me, and I caused the widdowes hart to reioyce. I put on Iustice and it couered me, my Iudgement was a Robe and a Crowne. I was the eyes to the blinde, and was feete to the lame, I was a father to the poore, and when I knew not the cause, I sought it out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentlie. I brake also the iawes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man, and pluckt the pray out of his teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:42"/>
            <p>The Iudge should be law to the sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The Noble, strength to the weake. The Minister, knowledge to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. The rich, meate and drinke to the hungrie. For rich men haue riches, not to spend epicuriously, but to reléeue those that néed. Learned men haue learning, to instruct the ignorant, and to féede Gods Church with the foode of knowledge. Wise men haue wisedome, not to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuent or deceiue the simple, but to stand with the simple against the subtle. Great men haue power and authoritie, not to beate their fellow seruants, and to oppresse the weake, but to beare vp the weake against the oppressors, to féede the Church of Christ. Christ said vnto <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 21. 15.</note>
               <hi>feed my sheepe, feed my Lambs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feed the flocke of Christ as much as lieth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5. 2.</note>
               <hi>in you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aring for is, not by constraint, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie, not for filthie lucre, but of a readie mind, not as though you were Lords ouer Gods inheritance, but that you may be examples to the flocke, and when the cheefe Shepherd shall appeare, you shall receyue an incorruptible crowne of glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the watchman▪ see the sword comming▪</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 33. 3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:43"/>
               <hi>and blowe the Trumpet, and warne the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: then he that heareth the sound of the Trumpet, and will not be warned, if the sword come and take him away, his bloud shall bee vpon his owne head. But if the watchman see the sword comming and take anie person from among them, he is taken awaie in his iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but his bloud God will require at the watchmans hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It lieth not in you to take sin from the people, and to make men religious and vertuous: but it lieth in you to blow the trumpets of Gods word, and to warne the people, that the sword of Gods wrath is comming, and tell them of their faults, and moue them to repentance. <hi>Paule planteth, Apollo watereth: but God</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 6.</note>
               <hi>giueth the increase.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You should not eate the fat, and cloth<note place="margin">Eze. 34. 3.</note> your selues with the woll: but you should rather strengthen the weake, and heale the sicke, bind vp the broken, bring againe that which is driuen away, and séeke out that which is lost. And to the deafe so become eares, to the blind eies, tungs to the dumb, féet to the lame, and helps to the helplesse. Men héereafter
<pb facs="tcp:16559:43"/> will giue you diuers names and titles, and call some of you Emperours, some kings, some Quéenes, some Dukes, some Earles, some Bishops, some Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Lawyers, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, some Ecclesiasticall, some ciuill: which names may not cause you to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine or neglect ech other, or contend one with another. But rather to draw in one line, remembring that though they be of seuerall callings, yet they be gifts all of one God, to moue you to take héed to your selues &amp; to all the flocke of Christ o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the which the holy Ghost hath made you ouerséers, to féed the Church of God.</p>
            <p>For reckon of what price the Church of God is, and how déere it must néeds be vnto God, that was made againe, and bought againe with his owne blood. <hi>We are not ransomed with corruptible siluer and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1. 19.</note>
               <hi>gold, but with the precious blood of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotted Lamb Christ Iesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God made man first a most glorious<note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> creature, an angell of light, full of truth and righteousnesse, but man made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe an ouglie féend of Hell, the child of Gods wrath and vengeaunce, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb facs="tcp:16559:44"/> prisoner in the bottomlesse lake,<note place="margin">Ephes. 2. 3. Matth. 13. 42. Mar. 9. 40.</note> where there is wéeping and gnashing of teeth, where the worme of conscience ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dieth, where the smoke of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments goeth vp for euer and euer.</p>
            <p>But Christ by his blood hath againe washed him from al his sinnes, and hath<note place="margin">Apo. 14. 11.</note> made him frée from death, Hell, sin, and<note place="margin">Apo. 1. 5.</note> Sathan, and brought him to fauour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with God his father.</p>
            <p>If the gold of <hi>Ophire,</hi> the precious stones and pearles of <hi>India,</hi> if all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures, and iewels, and vertues of heauen and earth, could haue made the price of our redemption, the sonne of God should neuer haue died. But our sinne was so great, the wrath of God so heauie, that nothing could satisfie both, but the death of the sonne of God. Great was the pain to be whipped, and scourged, and crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with thornes, greater were the paines to be nailed to the crosse, and pearsed to the hart with a speare. But the paines that caused the sonne of God to sweate water and bloud, the paines that caused the sonne of God to crie out as it were doubtingly, <hi>O God my God why
<pb facs="tcp:16559:44"/> hast thou forsaken me:</hi> could not all the creatures of heauen and earth, neither all the tungs of heauen and earth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse. Much must it néeds be that made the sonne of God sorie, more that made the sonne of God lament, but that that caused him to vtter these as it were doubting words, O God my God, why hast thou forsaken me, can no hart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. Surely, surely, euen then did he at one instant féele and beare the whole masse of Gods wrath, &amp; the whole masse of paine &amp; torment which all the elect of God shold for euer haue felt &amp; borne, if he had not made thē againe with his bloud. Consider that nature bindeth you to loue your like, that God hath placed you in authority, &amp; giuen you goodly gifts, &amp; that to féede and help the people of God. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider how great y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> price of their redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, how déere they must néeds be vnto their God that bought them so deere, how straight an account he wil require of you for such precious treasures. And you shal sée that you haue good cause not to mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend one hour, but in taking héed to your selus, &amp; the whole flock of Christ, wherof
<pb facs="tcp:16559:45"/> the holy Ghost hath made you ouerséers, to féede them with Gods holy word and good discipline.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, Sathan will thrust in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you rauening Wolues and profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed enemies, which after they haue dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen you with hookes, whipped you with scourges, haled you with racks: will burne you to ashes, cast you into the sea, starue you to death, crucifie you with your héeles vpwards, teare you in péeces with wild horses, tie one of your féete to your head, and set you ouer a soft smokie fire vntill you be choked, cut off your eares, noses, lips, hands and féete, put sharp thornes vnder your nailes, boile you in leade, cast you to wilde beasts to be deuoured, or burie you quicke, or trie you with some such extreme torments.</p>
            <p>Or else raise vp amongst you false bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, pretending to be Gospellers, to be zealous in the word, to be good in life, as <hi>Montanists, Nouatians, Manichees, Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians, Nestorians, Arrians,</hi> and such <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists</hi> and <hi>Libertines,</hi> which will bend and how the Scriptures to maintaine their monstrous errours. Some that
<pb facs="tcp:16559:45"/> Christ is not the sonne of God, some that Christ is not man, some that Christ did not suffer, some that the bodies doo not rise againe, some condemning mariage, some taking away the benefit of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, some taking Magistrates of the common wealth, and making all alike, some blaspheming the Sacraments, some holding that whoredome is no sin, theft is no sin, murther no sin in them, and infinite such like, which they deuise and faine of their owne heads, puffed vp with vaine glorie to get themselues a name, and that the changeable people may flocke to their sermons, and their lectures, and their churches, and their discipline, drawne and fed with theyr fond nouelties, whereof the simple be too too desirous.</p>
            <p>Though you shall be tried, not onely with the fell force of forraine foes, but also with the contentious, vaineglorious and dissembling brethren, yet may you not therefore shrinke, but looke vpon and follow the constancy of your forefathers.</p>
            <p>Both the Wolues of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed enemies <hi>Amelech, Midian, Edom</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16559:46"/> and <hi>Moab</hi> did trouble <hi>Moses,</hi> and also the vaine-glorious dissembling <hi>Israelites, Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> which rose vp against <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> and said vnto them. <hi>You take too much vpon you, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16. verse. 3.</note>
               <hi>all the congregation is holy, euery one of them: and the Lord is amongst them. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then lift you vp your selues aboue the congregation?</hi> And some of you shall not only be troubled with superstitious <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> but much more with vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Dathan,</hi> who séeketh equalitie and communitie, alleaging that the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation is holy euery one of thē, and that the Lord is among them, that they haue all the holy Ghost and the same spirit of God, that God is not tied to one more then another, and therfore neuer a one to be aboue other. Neither may thys bréede a doubt in your heads of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, when you shall sée so many sects, schismes, and diuersities of opinions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen amongst those that professe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> word: no more then when the good farmer hath sowed in his well tilled ground good wheate, he will condemne his wheate &amp; his ground when he séeth wéeds growe
<pb facs="tcp:16559:46"/> amongst it. You know y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> great houshol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<note place="margin">Math. 13. verse. 30.</note> did not only spy Tares growyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his wheat sowed by the enuious man: but also gaue charge to suffer them to growe vntill the haruest.</p>
            <p>Nay rather, assure your selues, that it is trueth and true Religion, because there be such Sects and diuersities of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. <hi>When the strong man armed kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 11. verse. 21.</note>
               <hi>the house: the things that he possesseth are in quiet.</hi> So long as the strōg possessed the Churche: so long all slept togither in peace and quiet, and dreamed the same fancyes. For your enimie Sathan that<note place="margin">Luc. 22. verse. 31.</note> sifteth you, is a subtle seruaunt, and knoweth too well what he hath to doe. He can playe the Fisher, whiche when he hath taken the Fish once sure in his nette: draweth it softlye, leaste hast shoulde braste the nette and let the fish goe. He can playe the Nurce, which when she hath rocked hyr Child asléepe, is quiet hir selfe, but if the Childe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waketh or cryeth, Then she rocketh and singeth as faste and as loude as she can. So Sathan, when he hath roc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and lulled his Children asléepe in
<pb facs="tcp:16559:47"/> idolatrie and ignorance is quiet inough. But when the voice of God awaketh them out of that sléepe, then beginneth he to rocke and stir himselfe againe. You may be sure that then he hath most cause when you sée him most busie.</p>
            <p>Neither can you haue a more certaine token of errour, then fleshlie concord. &amp;c. Neither can you haue a more certaine token of Gods truth, then that you spie Sathan angrie, stirring debate, and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the tares of varietie of opinions. And what is it now adaies that can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger him, but the truth and the Gospell of Christ preached, against which he ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all his force and might, and vseth all meanes possible, though he cannot ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, to deface it?</p>
            <p>The seruant may not be in better<note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 16 Luc. 2. 7.</note> case then his maister. Your maister Christ was borne in a stable, wrapt in a few rags, and laied in the maunger of the Oxe and the Asse, for there was no roome for him in the Inne. Rich men may lodge in the Inne of this world, they may liue in honour, in ease and pleasure. But the good Christians must
<pb facs="tcp:16559:47"/> liue in the stable, and must be swadled in the rags of reproch, contempt, and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. For hée that will not bée partaker with Christ in his rags of infamie, shall neuer be partaker with Christ in his robes of glorie, as himselfe saith. <hi>He that will be my Scholer, let him denie himselfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16. verse. 24.</note>
               <hi>take vp his crosse and follow me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Meruaile not, if yée shall sée professors of errour rich, honoured; renowmed in this world. But those that preach and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer the most precious pearle the word of God, the key of our saluation, be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and despised, that euery lewde fellow may speake, and doo his pleasure to them, and be borne out by one <hi>Mache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile</hi> or other, for the world loueth their owne, but the children of God it doth hate. And the children of God can no more liue in the honour and renowme of this world, then sugar be preserued in vinagre, or salt in the sea.</p>
            <p>But you will say, all these things trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs neuer a whit, for by Gods grace we are sufficientlie armed to stand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them all. But this only troubleth vs, that you <hi>Paule</hi> go from vs, and doo not
<pb facs="tcp:16559:48"/> leaue vs, or promise vs to send vs ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Paule,</hi> or doo not refer vs to some vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible teacher, or Church, whose iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we may stand and trust to. For as you say so we knowe that Sathan auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched scripture, that the <hi>Libertines</hi> auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched<note place="margin">Math. 4. 6</note> Scriptures, that Antichrist will bring Scripture, the <hi>Arrians</hi> will bring Scripture. And an hundred kind of secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and hereticks, will bend and bowe the Scriptures to drawe men to theyr sort, and many of them will be men of great learning, wit and authoritie.</p>
            <p>If Scripture be brought againste Scriptures, and learned men vrge them against learned men, whome shall the simple and vnlearned sort of vs trust t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or to whome doo you refer vs? to neuer a else of you all, <hi>But I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to finish his building, and to giue you an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance amongst his blessed Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Christ with his naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die was to leaue the world, and to depart from his disciples, they were sorie in the selfe same respect that you be, that they should want their faithfull visible guide
<pb facs="tcp:16559:48"/> and head. Christ comforteth them, not telling that he would leaue either <hi>Peter, Paule, Iames</hi> or <hi>Iohn</hi> in his place, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with sending them to any visible teacher, or any visible Church. But by telling them that he would send the holy<note place="margin">Iohn. 14. verse. 16. Iohn. 16. verse. 13.</note> Ghost, the spirit of truth to be their guide and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omforter, and his vicar generall in all truth.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Paule</hi> departing from you, leaueth you &amp; referreth you, neither to <hi>Titus,</hi> nor <hi>Timothe,</hi> nor to <hi>Barnabas, Silas, Marke,</hi> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> nor to the Church of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oche, Ephesus,</hi> or <hi>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nthus,</hi> nor to the Church of <hi>Hierusalem, Roome</hi> or <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua,</hi> nor to any visible Church that hath béene from the beginning of the world▪ or shall be to the end of the world. But I commend you to God the holy Ghost, and the word of his grace and mercie, which hath builded you vpon the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Eph. 2. 20.</note> of the Apostles and Prophets, the rocke Christ Iesus the sonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God. Therefore looke euer to this foundation which Christ layde, saying: <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> that is, Rockie, <hi>and vpon</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 16. verse. 18.</note>
               <hi>this Rock</hi> which thou hast cōfessed, saying,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:49"/> (<hi>thou art Christ the sonne of the liuing God) I will build my Church, and the gates of hell shall not preuaile against it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the only immouable founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">Hil. lib. 6. de Trin.</note> this is the only happy rocke of faith confessed by the mouth of <hi>Peeter. <hi>Thou art the sonne of the liuing God,</hi>
               </hi> bearing so much the certaintie of truth, as peruerse que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions and godlesse quarrels shall be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. This faith is the foundation of the<note place="margin">Hil. lib. 6. de Trini.</note> Church, by this faith the gates of hell are weake against it, this faith hath the keies of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            <p>He did not say vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> for he did<note place="margin">Chri. ser. de Pent.</note> not build his Church vpon man, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faith and confession of <hi>Peter</hi> what was this faith and confession? <hi>Thou art Christ the sonne of the liuing God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We that be and are called Christians,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 18. ca. 54. de ciuit. dei.</note> beléeue not in <hi>Peter,</hi> but in him in whom <hi>Peter</hi> beléeued. Christ, the same maister of <hi>Peter</hi> which leadeth to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting, he is our maister.</p>
            <p>This thing confessed by <hi>Peter,</hi> doth<note place="margin">Ambr de incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni cap. 5.</note> not onlie abandon one heresie: but wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Church like a good ship is tossed with many waues of the sea, the same
<pb facs="tcp:16559:49"/> must be the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> against al heresies. A day would not suffice to recite the names of heretinks; and heresies. Yet against them al staudeth this faith, that Christe is the Sonne of God, both eternall from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther▪<note place="margin">Irenaeus li. 2 ca. 59</note> and borne of the vil gilt.</p>
            <p>To build vpon the scripture, which is the certain &amp; vndoubted troth: is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ild the house vpon the strong and sure rock. But to leane that and to build vpon any other kinde of doctrine whatsoeuer it be: is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ild vpon the sinking sand.</p>
            <p>If so be the conduit of water doe suddē<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Ciprian.</note> faile men go to the heade, that there they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ray learne the cause of the default. And so should the ministers of god do, fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing the commandements of god, that af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ueth begin in any point to slacke: we should haue recourse vnto the originall of the lawe and the Gospell, and writings of the Apostles. That the triall of things may flowe from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, from whence the order and original doth spring. For the people of God is to be commended to god and to the grace of his word, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to finish the buildings.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:50"/>
            <p>If you had béene builded by man, or vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Mat. 8. 26.</note> the sand, the tempests and stormes of hell and the worlde might haue shaken you. But the foundation is Christe, the sonne of the liuing God. The woorkman is the holy Ghoste. And the woorde of his grace and mercy is the toole, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument. You saw the light of the law much dimmed after the death of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and other good kings, by the captiuities of <hi>Babilon, Caldaea</hi> and <hi>Assiria,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse warres and contentions that follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed.</p>
            <p>But God sent his sonne to reere it vp a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gain. You shal sée it much dimmed by the Romain Bishops: but God shall make it shine again the time appointed.</p>
            <p>Doe you fast much, pray much, watche much read the scriptures much, and care not for all their Schismes and sects, stor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and persecutions, and diuersities of opinions. For God that begon to builde your soules for his tēples, will finish the woork, and wil reueal so much of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> truth of his word vnto you, as shall be sufficiēt for you.</p>
            <p>The God that said vnto <hi>Abraham, <hi>Feare
<pb facs="tcp:16559:50"/> not Abraham, I am thy buckler and thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great reward.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The God that saide so Israel: <hi>Feare not, I haue redeemed thee, I haue called thee by thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 43. 1.</note>
               <hi>name, thou art mine Whē thou passest through vvater I vvill be vvith thee, and through the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ddes, that they doo not ouerflow thee. When thou walkest through the fire; thou shalt not be burnt? neither shall the flame kindle vppon thee. I am the Lord thy God, the holy one of Israell, thy sauiour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 44. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The God that saith to <hi>Iacob: <hi>Feare not Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob my seruant, and thou righteous, whome I haue chosen, for I will poure water vppon the thirstie, and fluds the dry ground. I will poure my spirit vpon thy seede, and my blessing vpon thy buds, and they shall growe as among the grasse, and as the willowes by the riuer of waters.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same God saith vnto you that he is your buckler, that the water &amp; waues of persecution shal not drowne you, neither the fire of dissentiō kindle vpō you▪ but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thirsty shal drink of the flud of his word, and his spirit shall blesse the séeds &amp; buds of al your words and déedes, &amp; they shall growe and flourish in his Church.
<pb facs="tcp:16559:51"/> And as you are required to reade Gods<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. 39.</note> word diligently, and to trust to it faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly: so be you to be admonished, not to bée too curious and too busy aboue your capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities. For God giueth faith and the spirit of knowledge by measure, To euery mā his peny and Ghomer, that is, inough,<note place="margin">Eph. 4. 7.</note> but not all alike.</p>
            <p>Let no man presume to vnderstand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that which is méete to vnderstand,<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 3</note> but that we vnderstand according to so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, as God hath delt to euery man the measure of faith.</p>
            <p>God hath giuen to one ten talents, to another fiue, to another one; some of you<note place="margin">Ma. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15</note> may vnderstand much, some lesse▪ &amp; some not so much.</p>
            <p>Trueth it is, that the holy Ghost is not tied to the schoole dores, and much lesse to the lawyers pen, or the merchāts wares or the artificers shops, yet as God hath his among the lawyers, among the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, among the merchants, and among all sorts of men: so learning is a goodly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strument in the Church of God, and a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary handmaid to the word of GOD
<pb facs="tcp:16559:51"/> and religion of god. About ships we trust the sea mens iudgement, The Lawyers about points of lawe.</p>
            <p>The Phisitions about medicines. And euery artificer about his worke. And let vs not thinke▪ but God blesseth their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures and trauailes▪ which spēd al their daies and times in prayer and studye of good learning.</p>
            <p>And as it is true that euery man may and ought to read or heare red, euery sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, branch, sentence, and word of scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture diligētly and painfully: so it is most true that euery one should not take vpon him the vnderstānding and expoundyng of euery scripture &amp; mistery of God and his word. For he which sawe Christ, and receiued the Gospel from Christ, doth cry out. <hi>O the deepenesse of the riches, both of the wisdome and knowledge of God. How vnsear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9 1. Gal. 1. 12. Rom. 9. 33</note>
               <hi>are his iudgements, and his waies past finding out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God shal furnish his Church with many good learned Fathers and Martirs, and yet god shal suffer them tō <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aile and slide in one point or other. God shall suffer thē to slide. First that they might knowe thē
<pb facs="tcp:16559:52"/> selues to be men. Secondlie that other may know them to be men &amp; not Gods. Now if the pillers of the Church, which haue the ten Talentes, and as it were the fulnesse of Faith and spirit, shall not attaine to the perfect knowledge and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of euery Scripture: much<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lesse shall suche as haue but fiue talents, and least of all, suche as haue but one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent attaine the same.</p>
            <p>So that Christians must become Bées which sit vpon euery flower, but neither doo take iuice out of euery flower, neither al the iuice out of such floures as they doo take some, but such and so much as shall suffice them to make Honye of. Euen so christians must sit on euery floure of the scripture, but neither take iuice out of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery flour, neither take al iuce out of such floures as they take some. But of suche floures, and so much as shall suffice euery one of them to make Hony according to their Talent, gift, and calling, to builde their part of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Princes and Counsailors which haue charge of euery one in the Realme, may not let Gods booke goe out of their sight,
<pb facs="tcp:16559:52"/> but must vpon it day and night. For they haue cure of much people; &amp; are to make much hony out of the floures of the word to féede them with.</p>
            <p>Nobles, Bishops and Iudges, that haue great diocesses and iurisdictions, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits, must read much in Gods booke, for they néede much Hony to féed the people vnder them with.</p>
            <p>Housholders must read so muche as wil serue them, their wiues, their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and al their seruants. For eache of them must be fed with so much hony out of Gods word, as wil teach them to feare God, obey their prince, loue theyr neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, and doo their dutie to their maister and other superiours. Neyther woulde God haue vs know al things in this life:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 2</note>
               <hi>for we know in part, and prophesie in part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs neuer require a reason of Gods doing, although many of them doe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Chris. ad Rom. ca 1</note> trouble vs. Only God is to command, the seruants must obey This is the pecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liar gift of faith, although we know not the manner of Gods purpose▪ yet to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the maiestie of his prouidence.</p>
            <p>Wee may not reprooue any thing in scripture which we doe not vnderstand:
<pb facs="tcp:16559:53"/> for there are many things that are not to<note place="margin">Ambr. li. de para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diso. ca. 2.</note> be measured by our capacitie: but by the déepenes of Gods purpose and word, It is better to be ignorant than to erre: but to vnderstand is better than to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.<note place="margin">Aug. sup. Ioh tract 21.</note> Therefore we ought to doo our best and vtmost to knowe if we can, the graces and goodnesses of God. And yet if we cannot knowe the trueth, let vs not fall into errour.</p>
            <p>As oft as you searche the mysteries of God, and shall find any doubte, haue a<note place="margin">Iustinus liber de trinitate.</note> redy solution for al douts and questions. I meane faith, remembring that when god shal do the déed, although something be vnknown, either for the excellencye of nature, or for the manner of the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, they that be ignoraunt shall take no hurt. Be religious and suppresse your doubts, neither let any thing satisfie▪ our doubts but only Faith. Be same, Gods word is true, although you doe not sée how.</p>
            <p>And if there happen any Scripture that seeme darke, or contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon course of beléefe and Faith: let them with the blessed Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> laye the
<pb facs="tcp:16559:53"/> same vp in their harts, and suspends their Iudgemēt, and think that it is either not<note place="margin">Luc. 2. 19.</note> néedfull for them to knowe any more, or els though God hath not yet, he wyll in time reuele vnto them the trueth.</p>
            <p>Some shal fal into distrust, and some into moste vaine fantasies vpon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption, that they must, may and do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand and truely expound euery place of scripture, aswell as the best learned man in the world: when as it were much more better for thē to suspend their iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments vntil god did open it, and yet euer to ancor vpon God, and the word of his grace, which is able and without per ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture will finish the building of hys Church and people in this world, and in the next world giue them an inheritance amongst all his blessed saints in euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting blesse and ioye. Otherwise if they wil be caried awaye with a Spirituall pride: they will run into infinite errors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God be mercifull vnto vs, and blesse vs, &amp;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 67. 1.</note>
               <hi>shew vs the light of his countenance and bee mercifull vnto vs,</hi> and graunt vs that the regard of our selues helth, may mooue vs to take héede to our selues, and the lawe
<pb facs="tcp:16559:54"/> to take héede to our neighboures, and the holy Ghost to both, to that end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, that as God hath indued euery one of yo with many goodly giftes, &amp; placed you in diuers kind of authorities: so may you féede and reléeue Gods people accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your talent, lest that the soules of christian men, the most pretious treasure made again with the blood of the lamb of God should perish by your default.</p>
            <p>And that such troubles as haue béene, or be, or may be, either from the rauening woolus, or crooked sectaries, may be spurs to quicken you to be carefull &amp; watchfull ouer your charge. And that you euer trust in God and his worde whiche is a strong buckler against all perils, and a sufficiēt warrāt to haue good successe, to finish the building of the church of god here in this worlde, and in the next world to inherit the kingdome of heauen, with al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Saints of God, the Father, the Sonne and the holy Ghost: to whom be al praise, &amp; honor and glory, nowe and euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16559:54"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>